<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints hope, and infalliblenes thereof. or Two sermons preached before the English companie at Middelb. about the moneth of October, 1608. Written by Mr. Iohne Forbes, at the earnest request of the hearers, and now published by them for the generall instruction and comfort of all Gods children</title>
            <author>Forbes, John, 1568?-1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115118</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850337</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850337</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 887:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints hope, and infalliblenes thereof. or Two sermons preached before the English companie at Middelb. about the moneth of October, 1608. Written by Mr. Iohne Forbes, at the earnest request of the hearers, and now published by them for the generall instruction and comfort of all Gods children</title>
                  <author>Forbes, John, 1568?-1634.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>126 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Schilders,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Middelborough :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The second sermon" has caption title; pagination and register continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177173:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177173:1"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS HOPE, AND INFALLIBLENES THEREOF. or Two Sermons preached before the Engliſh Companie at <hi>Middelb.</hi> about the moneth of October, 1608.</p>
            <p>Written by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohne Forbes,</hi> at the earnest requeſt of the hearers, and now publiſhed by them for the generall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and comfort of all Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Middelborough,</hi> by <hi>Richard Schilders,</hi> 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177173:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177173:2"/>
            <head>To his deare and welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved in the Lord, the faithfull En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Companie at <hi>Middelburrough,</hi> increaſe of wiſdome and grace from God the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt be multiplied.</head>
            <p>YOur earneſt requeſt in the Lord (moſt heartely beloued in him) was, that I would put in writte to you thoſe firſt Sermons, which, at the will of God, I preached amongſt you. J confeſſe that I am obliged to you all, in all duties of love, becauſe of the abundance of your love to me, or rather to the Lord Ieſus. Therfore, although the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of my weaknes &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie did ever, till this houre, hold me back fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> writing or prese<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting in writte any of my weake labours to the vſe of any yet, I could not reſiſt your lawful &amp; earneſt deſire in this particular; praying God to direct it to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie &amp; your comfort. Receive the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt two conceaved in ſubſtance as I deliuered them, but in larged according to the ſpeciall conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which it pleaſed the Lord to miniſter vnto my owne heart out of this Scripture, in time of my moſt heavie ſickenes, when J was dayly in hope to goe out of this body to dwell with the Lord. If yee finde any comfort in them, give all the glory to him who is able by
<pb facs="tcp:177173:3"/>the mouth of Babes and Sucklings, to make perfect his prayſe. And not ſtaying as Babes vpon the vſe of this milke, goe on in ſtrength by the ſolide comfort of that ſtrong meate, which yee have abundantly in the Lords great mercie dayly miniſtred vnto you, by the painfull labours and faithfull watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of your louing and learned Paſtour, whom the Lord hath taught to be a Scribe in his kingdome, a faithfull and wiſe ſteward to give his children their portion of meate in ſeaſon, at whoſe mouth receiving that ſincere milke of the word, ye ſhall doubtles grow vp to be a ſpirituall houſe &amp; an holy Prieſthood to God by Ieſus Christ our Lord, whoſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial bleſſing J pray for to his worke amongſt you, that you to your Pastour, and he to you, may be a ioy, a glorie, and a crowne of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the preſence of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt at his comming, whoſe grace, mercie and peace be with you all. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord M. I. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:177173:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. Epiſt. of Peter Cap. 1. verſe 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who according to his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant mercie, hath begotten vs againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a lively hope, by the reſurrection of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus from the dead.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is moſt true which the Apoſtle ſaith to the Corinths,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15:19.</note> that <hi>if in this life only wee haue hope in Christ, wee are of all men the moſt miſerable.</hi> For in al outward things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this preſent life, the wicked, for the moſt part, are in much better caſe then the godly; who dayly bearing the croſſe, through many tribulations and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, do enter in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. This being a thing neceſſarie,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.17. 2. Tim. 2.12</note> that whoſoeuer ſhall reigne with Chriſt, muſt firſt ſuffer with him. For there is no other way whereby the members can enter into glorie, but the ſame by which the Prince of ſaluation was conſecrate. Herefore it is that the Apoſtle in this Epiſtle, being to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort the Saints to conſtancie in holines &amp; patient bearing of all afflictions, doth lay the foundation of his doctrine, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the way to this Exhortation, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting before their eyes the hope of eternall life in Heauen with God:
<note n="*" place="bottom">The fight of things inviſible ſuſtaine the Saints in this life.</note> Knowing that in this life there is nothing, no not the very
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177173:4"/>inward beginnings of grace, and ſenſe of the goodnes and bountifulnes of God, &amp; of the peace &amp; ioy ſpirituall, that is able to vpholde the Saints in ſuffering for Chriſt, if they had no eſperance of greater and more excellent things after this life in the world to come. Therefore it is that in the Scriptures the ſpirit leadeth the Saints al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to the ſight of the glory that is to be manifeſted, to the Price of their high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Ieſus, and to the recompence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward laid vp for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the heauens:
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.10 &amp;c.</note> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the dayly bearing about of the dying of our Lord in our bodies, and in the dayly decay of the outward man, wee were not able to endure without fainting, if we did not caſt our eyes vpon things inviſible and eternall,
<note place="margin">Act. 7.55.</note> and not vpon things viſible which periſh. It was the ſight of the glory of God, and of Ieſus at the right hand of God that made <hi>Stephan</hi> to endure ſtoning to death: It was the ſight of him who is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, and of the recompence of reward which made <hi>Moſes</hi> to deſpiſe the wrath of <hi>Pharao,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.24</note> &amp; to eſteeme the reproach of Chriſt greater riches then the treaſures of <hi>Aegipt.</hi> The thing which did ſuſteine <hi>Iob</hi> in his greateſt miſeries,
<note place="margin">Iob. 19.26.</note> was the hope and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance he had that he ſhould ſee God in his fleſh, although that after his skin, wormes ſhould deſtroy his body: even that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould ſee him, &amp; that his eyes ſhould beholde him &amp; none other for him.
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> Chriſt Ieſus our Lord himſelfe endured the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177173:4"/>croſſe and deſpiſed the ſhame, for the ioy which was laid before him. According to which examples we muſt alſo indevour to holde the eyes of our minde fixed vpon Ieſus the authour and finiſher of our faith, where he ſitteth at the right hande of the Father crowned with glory and honour; waiting ſtil for our bleſſed hope, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the very Creature waiteth for,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.19</note> and in waiting groneth and laboureth in paine, becauſe it alſo is ſubdued vnder hope, that it alſo ſhalbe delivered from the bondage of corruption in that day. This is the cauſe wherefore the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in this place doth ſpeake ſo much of this hope: even that, as he himſelfe exhorteth vs, wee may gird vp the loynes of our mindes and bee ſober, and truſt perfectly, or to the ende in the grace which is brought to vs in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of Ieſus Chriſt, putting on, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth vs,
<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.8.</note> the hope of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for our helmet.</p>
            <p>In ſetting downe this hope, the Spirit of God for our further comfort and the more ſtrong inforcing of the exhortation buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereupon, doth meete the chiefe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations which may aſſault our weakenes in the troubles which accompanie the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truth: of which three are tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in the word which we haue read. The one concerneth Life it ſelfe: the other the Qualitie and Condition of that life: the laſt the Certaintie and Aſſurance of it. So firſt becauſe the Apoſtle did knowe howe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177173:5"/>hard and difficill a thing it is to perſwade man to forſake this preſent world, the life, the glory, the riches, the reaſt &amp; pleaſures of it, except hee have eſperance of an other world, life, glory, riches &amp; pleaſure. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth hee firſt ſet downe the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding mercie and goodnes of God in beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs to the hope of life in the heavens. Secondly, in reſpect the naked hope of an other life is not ſufficient to perſwade vs to forſake this life, nor to miniſter ſolide ioy in ſuffering for it, except we know that this life for which we hope, be much more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and precious. Therefore in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place the Apoſtle deſcribeth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of this life hoped for. Thirdly, ſeeing for the ſolide conſolation of the Saints, it is required that not only they have hope of life and knowe the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of it, but alſo that they bee ſure not to be fruſtrat nor diſappointed of their hope. Therefore in the third place hee declareth the certaintie &amp; infalliblenes of this hope. In theſe three points conſiſts the ſubſtance of the worde which wee have read: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee are now to ſpeake, as the Lord ſhal aſſiſt by his grace.</p>
            <p>But firſt of all before we enter to ſpeake of theſe three,
<note place="margin">Gods bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits never to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred without thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> we muſt conſider the maner which the Apoſtle vſeth in propounding of them, which is by way of thankſgiving. To teach vs in what maner wee ſhould ſpeak of the bleſſings of God, whoſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to vs ſhould never be reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177173:5"/>out thankeſgiuing to him. Hee chooſeth vs: he predeſtinateth vs: he calleth vs,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.6.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle, to the praiſe of the glory of his grace. Therefore when ever it pleaſeth him to beſtow vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs the fruits of his love, and free grace in Ieſus Chriſt: wee ſhould alwaies receiue them, thinke and ſpeake of them, ſo as our God receive of vs the thing for which hee giveth them, that is the prayſe of his glorious grace, wherwith he doth abound towards vs in all ſpirituall bleſſings in Ieſus Chriſt. There is a great difference betwixt the maner of ſpeech of thoſe who ſpeake vpon a bare and naked knowledge of the bleſſings of God, and of thoſe who ſpeake from the ſenſe &amp; feeling of them, as having taſted themſelves of the goodnes and bountifulnes of God in theſe bleſſings towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt. The ſpeech of the one as it is without feeling, ſo is it fectles and without force: they can ſpeake of his goodnes and not give him glorie: whereas the other are forced by their fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to glorifie God becauſe he is good, his love in their hearts conſtrayning them, as ſaith the Apoſtle.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.14</note> This is the cauſe why the Saints in Gods word have made ſo many ſongs of praiſe and thankſgiuing to God: ſo ſweete is the ſenſe of his mercie, and ſo deepe was the inſight they had of it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves, that they have provoked all the creatures to praiſe him, becauſe hee is good, and his mercie endureth for ever: as though themſelves alone were not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177173:6"/>to ſpeake of the praiſe of his grace towards them, yea the helpe of al creatures being too too ſmall in their iudgement to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worthely to render him the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his goodnes to them alone: &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their tongues and lips were not able condignely to thanke him, they haue called on their ſoules and all that is within them to prayſe his holy name. This ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for a tryal to vs to examine ourſelues in what ſort wee poſſeſſe the knowledge of the grace of God towardes man in Chriſt. Surely, it is to be feared that there is ſmall ſenſe &amp; lively feeling of it within vs, when thankfulnes doth not outwardly abound in our ſpeeches and actions. And hereby may we iuſtly eſteeme this age, although it abound in knowledge, yet to haue ſmall feeling of the things knowen, ſeing the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of men are ſo ſlenderly touched with the loue of God and his goodnes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heart nor tongue being prepared to proclayme his prayſe. The Prophet ſaith, and ſo doth the Apoſtle, <hi>I beleeved and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſpoke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.13</note> ſurely where faith is, there wilbe ſpeech. The Apoſtle therefore writing to the Coloſſians bids them abounde in faith with thankſgiuing.
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.7.</note> The ſame Apoſtle wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to make vs vnderſtand what is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of true knowledge, after hee hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted vs to know the will of the Lord, &amp; to be filled with the Spirit, he ſubioynes an exhortation to practiſe the effects of this knowledge, and amongſt the reſt hee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177173:6"/>vs alwayes to giue thanks for al things to God the Father in the name of Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, ioyning theſe two things together, and teaching vs that no bleſſing, yea nothing ſhould happen to vs for the which we ſhould not giue thankes to God. For that is the nature of true grace truly ingraffed in the heart for all things, even for Afflictions to prayſe the Lord. Let vs looke on the example of <hi>Iob,</hi> when God did permit Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpoyle him of his ſubſtance,
<note place="margin">Iob. 1.21.</note> his ſpeech is, <hi>The Lord hath given, and the Lord hath taken it, bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde hee acknowledgeth that it was the Lord that did giue, &amp; it was the Lord that did take, and hee bleſſed the Lord both in giuing him and in taking from him. If then the very Afflictions &amp; chaſtiſements, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Lord exerciſeth the faith and tryeth the patience of his Saints, bee iuſt matter both of reioycing, as Iames ſaith,
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.2.</note> and alſo of thankſgiuing: how much more ſhould we render thanks to God for our Election, our Calling, our Iuſtification, and all the reſt of his bleſſings both ſpirituall and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilie. Let vs learne then with the Apoſtle and according to the former exhortation of <hi>Paul,</hi> to give thanks alwayes for al things to God the Father in the Name of Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. So much concerning the maner of the Apoſtles ſpeaking and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding this bleſſing. Now wee come to the matter it ſelfe, which wee diuided in three, wherof the firſt concerneth the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177173:7"/>of God beſtowed vpon vs. In decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this bleſſing, wee haue theſe points ſet downe by the Apoſtle in order, 1. The Authour and giuer of it, to wit <hi>the God and Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> 2. The cauſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him to call vs to ſo excellent a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, to wit, his <hi>aboundant mercie.</hi> 3. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiue &amp; fitting mindes, wherby he both makes vs able for the benefite, and brings vs to it, to wit, <hi>The begetting of vs againe.</hi> 4. The bleſſing it ſelfe, to wit, <hi>a liuing hope,</hi> or <hi>the hope of life.</hi> 5. And laſt, the ground and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this hope, to wit, <hi>the Reſurrection of Christ from the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now concerning the firſt, it is the Father who is the Authour of this bleſſing, as he is the God &amp; Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Therefore doth the Apoſtle ſo deſcribe him in this place.
<note place="margin">The Father to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as God and Father of Chriſt.</note> In the which there are two things to be noted. 1. That the Father muſt be the God and Father of the Sonne, before we obtaine this bleſſing. 2. That the Sonne muſt be our Lord befor the Father, being nowe both God and Father to the Sonne, doe beſtow vpon vs this bleſſing. The firſt teacheth vs that our Adoption, Calling, &amp;c. are in and for Chriſt, not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply as he is God, nor ſimply as hee is man, but as he is both God and man, and ſo Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator betwixt God and man: for as hee is man, the Father is his God, and ſo doth he himſelfe cal him <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me:</hi> and as hee is God, the Father is his Father from all eternitie. The ſecond
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177173:7"/>teacheth vs that wee muſt bee of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of theſe who are giuen by the Father to the Sonne, and for whom the Sonne hath dyed to deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the handes of their ennemies, that they ſhould ſerue him without feare al the dayes of their life in holines and righteouſnes before him:
<note place="margin">Luc. 1.74.</note> both theſe are euident in the wordes. The firſt in that hee giueth thankes to God (for ſo it ſhould bee reade) and Father of Chriſt for this bleſſing of hope. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond in that he ſtyles Chriſt our Lord: both conteine not only rare &amp; wonderfull my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, but matter of moſt ſingular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort and neceſſary inſtruction to all Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak a litle of the firſt, it is a matter of great admiration to ſee the love of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toward ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo great that he would haue his Sonne abaſing himſelfe ſo for mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, that he would have him become a ſeruant and ſubiect to obedience as other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So ſpeaketh the Father by the Prophet: <hi>Behold my ſeruant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 42.1.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſtay vpon him mine elect in whom my Soule delighteth:</hi> &amp; not only that, but much more that which him ſo abaſed, hee would eſtabliſh his couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be the God &amp; Father of Chriſt as hee is man, all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind hauing loſt that felicity in the fall of <hi>Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> ſo that in Chriſt Ieſus,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 7.14 conferred with Heb. 15.</note> the man bleſſed for euer, the Father beginneth to be a God &amp; Father to mankind againe. Next in this point is to be admired the wonderful loue of the Sonne to man,
<note place="margin">Philip. 2.6.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>who being in the forme of God, thought it no robbery to be equall with God, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177173:8"/>he made himſelfe of no reputation, and tooke on him the forme of a ſeruant, and was made like vnto men, and was found in ſhape as a man; hee humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and became obedient vnto the death, even the death of the Croſſe.</hi> Hereby it cometh to paſſe that the Sonne of God becometh our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; ſo we againe, in Gods infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.25. conferred with Heb. 12.</note> reſtored to the dignitie of the Sonnes of God in Chriſt, who hauing taken parte with vs of fleſh &amp; blood, was not aſhamed to call vs brethren, vs I ſay, whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had given him:
<note place="margin">Iſay. 8.18. conferred with Heb. 2.13.</note> and alſo the children of God. Behold, here am I and the children which God hath giuen me. Thus nothing in the world ſhould more reioyce our hearts then the incarnation of the Sonne of God,
<note place="margin">Luc. 2.14.</note> by the which glorie came to God in the higheſt heavens, peace in the earth, and goodwill towards men: and by the which God became to be with vs: therfore was he called <hi>Emanuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 7.14. &amp; Math. 1.23.</note> for the true taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of God became to bee with men when the Sonne of God became man. The vſe for our inſtruction of this firſt point is threefold.
<note place="margin">No ſaving knowledge nor ſight of God but in Chriſt.</note> 1. Wee muſt hereby learne that God maketh his covenant of grace imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly, and firſt with his Sonne made man: for this is the worde of the covenant, <hi>I wilbe your God, and yee ſhalbe my people:</hi> and in the place before cited out of the 2. of Sam. cap. 7 <hi>I wilbe his Father, and he ſhalbe my Sonne.</hi> Thus none in all the world of all the poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> was worthy, with whom the Lord ſhould enter in covenant, but his Sonne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177173:8"/>in whom it is that wee are made the children of God, hee firſt becoming our brother. Thus it is evident that we cannot have the Lord to be either God or Father to vs, but in Chriſt. Therefore he ſendeth this Meſſage with <hi>Marie</hi> to his Diſciples, as the moſt comfortable that he could ſende after his Reſurrection:
<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.17.</note> 
               <hi>Goe to my Brethren and ſay to them, I aſſende to my Father, and your Father; to my God and your God.</hi> Therefore the nature of true faith is alwayes to looke to God in Chriſt, &amp; to behold all bleſſings comming from the Father in and for Chriſt, &amp; to ſee God to be a God &amp; a Father in him alone: ſo that who looketh not to God in Chriſt, can ſee nothing in him to comfort them, but by the contrary they muſt ſee him ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with wrath and iuſtice to their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting confuſion as their Iudge and not as their God. The ſecond is that they doe not know God aright vnto ſalvation, who only know him as the Father of the Sonne, and doe not knowe him as their God:
<note place="margin">The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the incarnation of the Son, neceſſary to Life.</note> for it is not ſufficient to know the myſterie of the Trinitie vnto Salvation, but wee muſt alſo know the myſterie of the humiliation of the ſecond perſon, whereby hee became a ſervant to the Father, &amp; the Father became his God. Therefore muſt we both learne to know the eternal generation of the Son as God equall with the Father: And that alſo whereof the Lord ſpeaketh in the 2. Pſalme: <hi>Thou art my Sonne, this day haue I begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thee.</hi> Whereby is vnderſtood the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177173:9"/>of the ſonne in the fleſh, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of him now to bee the Sonne of God. The third vſe is, to know the diuers grounds of Gods diſpenſation of his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites to man, which are two: The firſt is in his Sonne, as Creator, Ruler, Vpholder of the world, in whom they are, they live, they mooue,
<note place="margin">Act 17.25. &amp;c.</note> and who giueth to al life &amp; breath, and all things: by which reaſon alſo all men are the generation of God, in reſpect of their creation. The ſecond ground of his diſpenſation is in his Sonne, as Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of the world, and Mediatour betwixt the Father and Man, being himſelfe both God and Man, and hauing the Father both God and Father to him, that hee might bring the reſt of the children giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him, not only to the dignitie of ſonnes againe, but alſo to the glorie. In which reſpect the elect, all the generation of God by regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and new birth, beſides that they are the generation of God with the reſt of the world, by creation, &amp;c. according to the diuerſitie of their groundes, ſo is the diſpenſation of God to men diuers. The firſt is, the ground of his diſpenſation, to the reprobates, yea to all his other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The ſecond is, the ground of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation to his elect. And becauſe the firſt ground concerneth this life: therefore is it that God beſtoweth on the reprobates, aboundance of earthly things, as riches, honour, kingdomes and Empires, and yet al in his wrath, becauſe they receyue them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177173:9"/>not in Chriſt, the only cauſe of his loue to man: &amp; ſo it ſhall come to paſſe, that many who haue moſt of this wordly wealth, rit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and pleaſures from God, ſhall neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles be caſt by him in hell fire: therefore we muſt not iudge of Gods favour to men by the outward bleſſings of this life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of all are partakers: for God maketh his ſunne to ariſe on the evill, and the good, and ſendeth raine on the iuſt and vniuſt.
<note place="margin">Math. 5.45.</note> The ſecond ground of Gods diſpenſation concerneth ſpeciallie the life to come (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the children of God haue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe both of this life and the life to come,) therfore is it that the Lord beſtoweth his love, his mercie, his grace, and all his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall bleſſings, to none, but ſuch as are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely members of Ieſus Chriſt his Sonne: who doe worſhip him in Chriſt his Sonne made man, who do come to him by Chriſt: who doe call vpon him in the name of Chriſt: who doe acknowledge Chriſt to be their wiſedome, their righteouſnes,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30</note> their ſanctification, and redemption. Therfore, we should ſtudie to haue part in Chriſt, if wee deſire to receiue from God eternall life: but more of this in the next point, to wit, that it behoueth Chriſt to be our Lord, before we receyue the bleſſings from God, which now followeth. In this point wee have to conſider: Firſt, how many wayes Chriſt is the Lord of Mankinde, and next in what ſenſe hee is called our Lord by the Apoſtles: As for the firſt, we finde him in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177173:10"/>the ſcriptures three maner of wayes Lord. Firſt,
<note place="margin">How many wayes Chriſt is Lord.</note> as wee haue God the Creatour of all things, in which reſpect, he is alſo Lord of all things: ſeeing all things receyued their being from him, and are ſuſtayned by the power of his worde. Concerning the firſt, in Pſalme 102.
<note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> Hee is called Lord: <hi>Thou O Lord from the beginning laydeſt the foundation of the earth, and the heavens are the workes of thy handes.</hi> Further it is ſaid concerning his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: <hi>Thy Throne O God is from euerlasting to euerlasting.</hi> And touching the ſame, and the ſecond alſo, in the firſt to the Hebrues it is ſaid, that by him God made the world: &amp; therafter, that he ſuſtaines all things by the mightie power of his worde. Secondly, he is called Lord as he is the ſonne of man:
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.18.</note> for euen as he is man, he hath receiued all power both in heauen and in earth,
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.10.</note> and is made the head of all principality &amp; power,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> and is crowned with glory and honour, and is ſett aboue all the workes of Gods handes,
<note place="margin">Heb. 2.7.8.</note> and hath all things put in ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnder his feete,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.4. and 10.11.</note> and hath a name giuen him aboue all names: that at the name of Ieſus,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.21.</note> ſhould every knee bowe, both of things in heauen and things in earth, and things vnder the earth:
<note place="margin">Iohn 17.2.</note> And that every tongue ſhould confeſſe that Ieſus Chriſt is the Lord, vnto the glorie of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And this dominion is generall ouer all fleſh, and aboue all principalitie and power, and might, and domination, and every name that is named. So that hereby
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177173:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>he is Lord of the very Diuels and of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates, no leſſe then of the godly and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect.
<note place="margin">Iohn 17.1.</note> But the end wherefore hee receiued this power, is not one to both: for to the elect it is that he may giue to them eternal life, but to the other it is that he may cruſh them with a ſcepter of yron,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.9 Reuel. 2.27</note> and breake them in pieces like a potters veſſell. Which is a great conſolation to all that are his members:
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 7.8 9.10.</note> knowing that all their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ts both bodily and ſpirituall are ruled by their Lord and Saviour, and that the heauens are his, and all that therein is: and the earth is his, and that therein is, So that nothing can be wanting to them that feare him. Laſtly, he is Lord ſpeciallie and only of his Saints and Church of God,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.25.26.27.</note> which he hath purchaſed to him ſelfe by his own blood.
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24. Coloſ. 1.14 Luc 1.71.72. and 73 74.75. Pſal. 2.6. Luc. 1.32. Epheſ. 1.22. Ioh. 10.19. Iohn 17.2. and 6 and 9.11.24. 1. Pet. 2.4. Heb. 2.5.</note> And therefore beſyde this generall Dominion which is giuen him ouer all creatures, he is ſpeciallie anoynted and ſet king vpon Sion, the Lordes holy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and hath receiued the throne of his father Dauid, to raigne ouer the houſe of Iacob for ever, and is made aboue all things, the head of the Church: in which reſpect the elect are ſaid, only to be giuen to him of the Father, whereas in reſpect of his general Dominion, all things are given him of the Father. This Dominion and Lordſhip conſiſteth in the Right that Chriſt hath to vs by his owne purchaſe: &amp; in the ſpirituall gouernement of his Saints by his ſpirit and word: Ruling thereby in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177173:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>their hearts, &amp; not ſuffering any more Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than nor ſin to beare rule in their mindes, but making them as a choſen generation: a Royall Prieſthood: an holy Nation: a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſet at libertie, to ſhewe foorth the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of him that hath called them out of darknes into his marvelous light: And this is the kingdome of Chriſt which is not of this world, but is called the kingdome of the world to come, becauſe it concerneth not the things of the world belonging to this earthlie and corruptible life, but the things that belong to the ſpirituall life of God in vs: in creating vs over againe to his Image,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.31</note> and making vs partakers of all the ſpirituall bleſſings that are in the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie places in Chriſt Ieſus him ſelfe. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is ſo called, becauſe it ſhall not be perfyted in this world, but in the world to come, when the ſhape and forme of this world ſhall be aboliſhed and paſſed away. Theſe are the three wayes that Chriſt is to be conſidered Lord in the ſcriptures. In the firſt reſpect, he is Lord with the Father and with the Spirit, and he is the very life of the world, in whom al things haue their naturall being and moouing, and ſo are bound for this very life to ſerue him. In the ſeconde reſpect hee is made Lord by the Father, who hath giuen him the pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence in all things aboue all creatures,
<note place="margin">Iohn 5.2.7.</note> that hee ſhould rule the world and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iudgement, as hee is the Sonne of Man. In which reſpect all knees muſt bow
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177173:11"/>to him, and euery mouth ſhalbe compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to confeſſe him the Lord, when all his enemies ſhalbe made his footeſtoole. In the third reſpect, hee is Lord by Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of vs out of the handes of Sathan and all our ſpirituall enemies, and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Fathers iuſtice for our ſinnes, appointed by the Father, and ſett ouer the houſe of God as the only Lord thereof: the only High Prieſt and Prophete. So that in this reſpect it is ſaid by the Apoſtle, <hi>that vnto vs, there is but one God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 5. &amp; 1</note> 
               <hi>which is that Father of whome are all things, and wee in him. And one Lord Ieſus Christ, by whom are all things, and wee by him.</hi> So that wee are to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no other Lord ouer vs, as wee are the houſe of God and members of the body of Chriſt, but Chriſt alone: ſince none but Chriſt alone hath bene crucified for vs.
<note place="margin">Heb. 3.4 and 6.</note> Therefore doth the Apoſtle ſhewe plainelie, that <hi>Moſes,</hi> who had the greateſt authority in the houſe of God, of any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man before the Apoſtle, and who was faithfull in all the houſe of God, that yet he was not Lord of the houſe, but in it was as a ſeruant: and that Chriſt only, as the Sonne, is ouer his owne houſe.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.5.</note> And the Apoſtle Paul, ſpeaking of himſelfe and the other Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">All creaturs obliged to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Chriſt their Lord</note> declared that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver preached themſelues to bee the Lords of the Saintes, but the Lord Ieſus to bee the Lord, and themſelues ſeruants to the Church for Chriſtes ſake. Nowe Chriſt being our Lord in all the three reſpectes,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177173:12"/>we haue to conſider the vſe hereof, and in which of the three he is here in this place called our Lord: By this doctrine it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, that whether we be of the number of theſe that haue no minde of any liſe but of this preſent life, whether we be ſuch as regard the courſe of this world, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of all the affaires of this life: or whether we be ſuch as haue our mindes lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp to the heauens in reſpect of the life to come: we muſt alway, at leaſt ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to reuerence Chriſt as our Lord ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheles if in the firſt degree we only ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor him, that is as he is the Authour of this mortall life, wee are no better then the beaſtes and moſt in ſenſible creatures, who in that reſpect in their owne kinde, doe glorifie him:
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.19.</note> yea we are more ſenceles then the ſenceles creatures, who with groning waite for the manifeſtation of the ſonnes of God. If in the ſecond reſpect, wee only acknowledge Chriſt our Lord, then are we in no better caſe then the reprobates, and Deuills themſelves, who haue confeſſed Chriſt the Lord,
<note place="margin">Act. 19.15.</note> and acknowledged his authoritie in begging libertie to enter in ſwyne before they durſt doe it:
<note place="margin">Mat. 8.29. and 31.</note> and in the end ſhall all bee compelled to confeſſe it. The ground, and comfort and cauſe of all true happineſſe, is, to haue Chriſt our Lord, in the third reſpect: and this is, when his ſpiritual kingdom is erected in our hearts, which ſtandeth not in meate nor drinke, nor any thing whereby this mortall life is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177173:12"/>maintayned, but in righteouſnes &amp; peace and ioye in the holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.17</note> ariſing vpon the aſſurance of the remiſſion of our ſinns, and iuſtification by faith in the blood of Ieſus, and this bleſſed hope of eternall life in the heauens. In this laſt ſenſe is it that here Chriſt is called our Lord, &amp; in reſpect of this Lordſhip and Dominion of Chriſt ouer vs, and in vs, is it, that wee receyue from the Father, this bleſſed hope: The ſence whereof maketh vs to render glorie, and honour, and thankes, and praiſe to him in Chriſt, as the Apoſtle here doth. In reſpect of which kingdome it is, that in the 97.98. and 99. Pſalmes, the ſea, the yles, the floods, &amp; Mountaines, are commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to reioyce, to ſing, to clap their hands, to praiſe him, to tremble and be moued at his preſence, and glorie of his power, and to exalt and worſhip him.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this doctrine is twoofolde: Firſt, it warneth vs to examine our hearts, if Chriſt haue come in to dwell in them, in righteouſnes, in peace, and ioy of the holy Ghoſt, and ſo haue made vs partakers of his death and life, and giuen vs the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of our inheritance, even the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of promiſe: then may we reioyce trulie, and then ſhall we haue iuſt reaſon to glorie in the hope of the glorie of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.2.</note> hauing peace with God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: Where by the contrarie, they that haue not Chriſt raigning in them, or will not haue him to raigne over them, after
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177173:13"/>the laſt reſpect: haue to looke for nothing but according to that which of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt is ſaide: That the Lord ſhall ſpeake to them in his wrath, and vexe them in his ſore diſpleaſure:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.5.</note> And according as it is ſaide by Ieſus himſelfe, that they ſhalbe brought and ſlaine before him.
<note place="margin">Luc. 14.27.</note> Therfore bleſſed are they that doe ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Goſpell of Ieſus, which is the ſcepter and ſword of his kingdome: and woe ſhalbe to all them that repine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond vſe of this point is, to teach vs to know, if our thankeſgiuing to God, be rightlie giuen, and if it proceed of the right ground. The Apoſtle to the Epheſians biddeth vs, <hi>that we giue thankes at all times and for all things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">8. phe. 5.20.</note> But to whom? <hi>To him,</hi> ſayeth the Apoſtle, <hi>who is God &amp; Father.</hi> And after what maner? that doth he alſo declare, ſaying: <hi>In the Name of our Lord Ieſus Christ.</hi> Whatſoeuer bleſſing then it be which we receiue from God, be it bodily or ſpirituall, concerning either this life or the life to come, we muſt acknowledge the giuer both God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: thanke him as God and Father, and that in the Name of Ieſus our Lord. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they doe not glorifie God aright by their thankeſgiuing, who do not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him to beſtowe theſe benefites vpon them as their God and Father in Chriſt, according to this covenant, and who in thankeſgiuing doe not glorifie God in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177173:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>name of Ieſus, as their Lord. For this cauſe the Apoſtle to the Coloſſians com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth vs:
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>that whatſoeuer wee doe in word or deed, wee doe it all in the name of the Lord Ieſus:</hi> and thereto more particularly hee addeth concerning thankeſgiuing: giving thankes to God the Father through him. To teach vs after what manner we ſhould thanke God aright for all things. And herevnto agreeth that which the Apoſtle to the Hebrues teacheth vs, when hee biddeth vs that wee ſhould haue grace in our heartes,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.28.</note> by the which wee may ſerue God ſo as hee bee pleaſed. For where Grace is not, and ſo by conſequence, where the knowledge of God in Chriſt is not, and the kingdome of Chriſt is not ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the heart, in righteouſnes, peace and ioy of the holy Ghoſt, there is no thankſgiuing proceeding from that heart, that can bee acceptable to God. No, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is done for his ſeruice, can be acceptable vnto him.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For as wee haue alreadie ſaid before out of the Pſalmiſt and other Apoſtles: <hi>I beleeved, therefore did I ſpeake,</hi> 2. Cor. Cap. 4. verſ. 13. the ſpeach to God, or of God. That which proceedeth not from faith, ſhall neuer bee accepted of him. Therefore is it that the Apoſtle biddeth vs, <hi>that wee ſhould abound in faith with thankeſgiuing,</hi> to informe vs, that all true thankeſgiuing muſt be accompanied with faith, and flowe therefrom.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:177173:14"/>
            <p> Thus much concerning this firſt point, that is the Authour of this benefite of a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vely hope. Nowe followeth the ſecond point, touching the cauſe moouing God the Father in Chriſt to begett vs to his hope, and that is his aboundant mercie.</p>
            <p>In this point,
<note place="margin">Mercie the only cauſe moouing God to cal vs.</note> we haue twoo things to be marked. The firſt is, the cauſe it ſelfe moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God to bring vs to his bleſſing, which is his MERCIE. The ſecond is, the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his mercie, which mooveth him to graunt this bleſſing, which ſtandeth in the meaſure of it, in that it is called, <hi>his aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant mercie.</hi> As touching the firſt, it plainly layeth downe before vs our owne miſeries: Firſt, in that we were ſuch as had need to be pitied, &amp; vpon whom the Lord ſhould haue compaſſion, as being in miſerable cace, and vnable to deliuer our ſelues from our miſerie: For where there is no helpe left but that which ſtandeth in the mercie of our Iudge, he alſo being our partie, the caſe muſt needes be moſt miſerable. Nowe it is playne by the Apoſtle, that if God had not had pittie and compaſſion on vs, wee had neuer attained, not ſo much as to any hope or eſperance of eternall life, ſeeing nothing els but his owne mercie and pitie did mooue him to call vs to this bleſſed hope: which is moſt plainly ſet downe by the Apoſtle to the Epheſians,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.3.4</note> in that hee maketh all men, both Iewe and Gentile by nature, to be the children of wrath; and the cauſe of our calling, regeneration and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetie
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177173:14"/>from that wrath, to bee the riches of Gods pitie and compaſſion, and the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his love. Secondly, this ſetteth before vs the nature of our God, that it is ſuch, as he himſelfe proclaimed, when hee made all his goods goe before Moyſes, and proclaimed the Name of the Lord before him, ſaying: <hi>The Lord, the Lord: ſtronge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 34.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and gracious: ſlowe to anger, and aboundant in goodnes and trueth: reſeruing mercie for thouſandes: forgiuing iniquitie and tranſgreſſion, and ſinne, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.5.</note> Therefore it is that Dauid hauing taſted of the mercie and kindnes of the Lord, doeth ſhewe foorth to the world the ſame,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</note> ſaying: <hi>The Lord is mercifull and righteous, and our God is full of compaſſion.</hi> And againe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.8.</note> 
               <hi>He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth but a whyle in his anger, but in his favour is lyfe. Weeping may abyde at euening, but ioy commeth in the morning.</hi> Alſo he inviteth the world to prooue how good the Lord is, Saying, <hi>Taſte ye and ſee how gratious the Lord is.</hi> And for this cauſe, doth Dauid take occaſion to praiſe the Lord, and to reſolve with him ſelfe to prayſe him in the ſaid 34. Pſalme:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>I will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way giue thankes vnto the Lord: his prayſe ſhalbe in my mouth continuallie,</hi> and doth inuite and wil all others to praiſe the Lord with him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Prayſe the Lord with mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 3.4.3.</note> 
               <hi>and let vs magnifie his Name together.</hi> And further hee doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue, to reioyce and glory in the Lord, &amp; in his mercie, ſaying: <hi>I wilbe glad and reioyce in his mercie.</hi> And againe: <hi>My ſoule ſhall glory in the Lord.</hi> And alſo exhorteth the righteous and Saints <hi>to loue the Lord, &amp; to reioyce in him, becauſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177173:15"/>of his mercie,</hi> ſaying in the 31. Pſalme: <hi>Loue the Lord all yee Saintes, &amp;c.</hi> And the 32. Pſalme and 11. verſe. <hi>Bee gladde yee righteous, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in the Lord, and bee ioyfull all yee that are vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in heart.</hi> And ſo in the beginning of the 33. Pſalme, and many other Pſalmes. The vſe of this poynt is: Firſt, to humble vs all before the Lord our God, as beeing ſuch who haue forfaited all felicitie, that there is no hope of bleſſednes,
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.22.</note> nor lyfe left vs, but in the mercie of God, againſt whom wee haue ſinned, for all are included vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſinne, that the promiſe by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, ſhould be giuen to them that beleeue:
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.32</note> And <hi>God hath ſhut vp all in vnbeleefe, that hee might haue mercie on all.</hi> So that wee muſt all confeſſe with the Prophete:
<note place="margin">Ier. lament. 3. and 22.</note> 
               <hi>That it is the Lords mercie, that we are not conſumed.</hi> And againe:
<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>Except the Lord of Hoaſtes had reſerued to him a ſmall remnaunt, wee ſhould haue bene as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſhould haue bene like to Gomora.</hi> For as the Apoſtle ſayeth:
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.9. and 23.24</note> 
               <hi>All both Iewe and Gentile are vnder ſinne: there is none righteous: no, not one, &amp;c. For all haue ſinned, and are deprived of the glorie of God, and are iustified freelie by his grace.</hi> Therefore let vs all learne to obey the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation and inſtruction given by God to vs, by the mouth of his Prophete, that is,
<note place="margin">Micah. 6.8.</note> to humble our ſelues: to walke with our God.
<note place="margin">Iem. 4.6.7.10.</note> And as the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>Let vs ſubmit our ſelues to God, for hee reſiſteth the proude, and giueth grace to the humble: Let vs caſt downe our ſelves before him, and hee will lift vs vp.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon doth follow the ſeconde vſe, which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177173:15"/>is, to conuince all them that put the cauſe of their ſaluation, or hope of ſaluation, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the power of their free will, or in the merite of their workes, or any other thing whatſoeuer, except in the mercy of God only. For God witneſſed of himſelfe in the Prophete Eſaie: <hi>I, euen I, am hee, that putteth away thine iniquities, for mine owne ſake,</hi> Eſa. cap. 43. verſ. 25. And the Apoſtle plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtifieth, <hi>that by grace wee are ſaued through faith.</hi> Epheſ. cap. 2. verſ. 8. And leaſt that any man ſhould thinke, that to beleeue were in his owne power, and did proceed from himſelfe, &amp; therefore that his ſafetie were of himſelfe, the Apoſtle addeth, <hi>and that not of our ſelues, it is the gift of God.</hi> And yet further to make it more cleare, hee ſubioyneth, <hi>that it is not of workes, that we are ſaued.</hi> And he giueth the reaſon twoofold. Firſt, <hi>leaſt any man ſhould boast himſelfe.</hi> For as the Apoſtle in an other Epiſtle affirmeth: All reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, all gloriation of man in himſelfe, is excluded, and that by the law of faith, and not of workes:
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.27. and 4.2.</note> for if our Iuſtice did come by our workes, then had we wherein to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce and glorie. And for this cauſe alſo is it, that God doth chooſe the vyle things of this worlde, the fooliſh and the weake,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 27. to the end</note> euen that no flesh should reioyce or glory in his preſence, for wee are that which wee are, of him in Chriſt Ieſus, and not of our ſelves, nor in our ſelves ſaith the Apoſtle, be it Wieſdom, iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſactification, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. That according as it is written.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177173:16"/>Hee that reioyceth, let him reioyce in the Lord.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon of the Apoſtle to the Epheſians,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> is, <hi>Becauſe the power of doing good, is not of our ſelues, nor in our ſelues, becauſe we are the workmanſhip of God, created to good workes.</hi> And this Creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſaith the Apoſtle) is in Chriſt Ieſus, &amp; therefore not in our ſelues. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not of our ſelues that we do good, but of God, <hi>who worketh in vs both the will and the deed, and that of his good pleaſure.</hi> Neither haue we the vertues in our ſelues of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good, but in Chriſt Ieſus, that we iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay with the Apoſtle to the Galathians,
<note place="margin">Gall. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>It is not we that liue any more, but Christ that liueth in vs.</hi> And therefore with the ſame Apoſtle to the Corinthians:
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.2 and 3.</note> Our reioycing ſhould be not in our ſelues, but in the man, which is Chriſt. And we ought to acknowledge with him, <hi>that what we are, we are it by the grace of God:</hi> And when we labour in well doing, <hi>it is not we, but the grace of God which is with vs.</hi> This ſerveth to vs for two things, to inſtruct vs, not with Papiſt or other whatſoeuer, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe merites to our workes, or to eſteeme the cauſe of our election, calling, iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or glorification to be in our ſelues or our workes, but in the free grace of God. Therfore doth the Apoſtle to the Romans, declare,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.5.</note> 
               <hi>that the remnant which are ſaved, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued according to the election of grace:</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon concludeth, that if election bee of grace, it is no more of workes, elſe were grace no more grace: And if it be of works,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177173:16"/>then it is no more of grace, or els, workes were no more works. So may we conclude here, of <hi>our calling to the hope of life:</hi> ſince the Apoſtle ſaith, It is of Gods abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, than it is not of merit, els were mercy no more mercy: and if it be of merite, it is no more mercy, or els merite were no more merite. The cauſe therefore moouing God to call and elect vs, is no wayes in vs, but in God himſelfe. Therefore doth the Apoſtle ſay to the Epheſians,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.5.</note> that God hath prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated vs to be adopted through Chriſt in himſelfe. And what was the cauſe in himſelfe moouing him, the Apoſtle like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe declareth it <hi>(According to the good pleaſure of his wil.)</hi> And moreouer in the next verſe, he maketh it more plaine, ſaying: That it is his grace wherewith hee hath made vs freely accepted in his beloved: &amp; yet more amplie, hee cleareth this, adding in the 7. verſe, That the redemption which we haue by the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>is alſo according to his rich grace.</hi> Declaring that whither wee look to God in giuing Chriſt to dye for vs, or whither wee conſider God iuſtifying vs in Chriſt, and accepting of vs in him for the merite of his death, applying or impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame to vs: There was, nor is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that mooueth him to doe ſo, but his owne grace. For as it is written,
<note place="margin">Exod. 33.19</note> 
               <hi>I will haue mercy vpon him, to whom I will ſhew mercie: &amp; wil haue compaſſion vpon him on whom I will haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. So that it is not in him that willeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.15. &amp; 16. &amp; 18</note> 
               <hi>nor in him that runneth, but in God that ſheweth mercie.</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:177173:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>And therefore hee hath mercy on whom hee will, and whom hee will, hardeneth.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that hereby we learne is, that comfortable leſſon which the ſpirit of God teacheth vs by the Apoſtle to the Romanes, reaſoning from this mercie and loue of God towardes vs in Chriſt, who when wee were yet of no ſtrength, at his time,
<note place="margin">Rom 5.6.7. &amp; 8.9.10.</note> dyed for the vngodly: God ſetting foorth his merueillous loue to vs, that whyle we were yet ſinners, Chriſt dyed for vs. Whereupon he concludeth, that nowe being iuſtified by his bloud, we ſhall much more bee ſaued from wrath through him. For as the the Apoſtle ſayeth. <hi>If when we were enemies, wee were reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 2.3.4 and 5.</note> 
               <hi>much more being re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciled, we ſhalbe ſaved by his life.</hi> For that mercy that mooued God when we were dead in ſinne and treſpaſſe, being by nature the children of wrath,
<note place="margin">Ier. lament. 3.22.</note> to quicken vs in Chriſt: Seeing it remained for euer, and his compaſſions fayle not, but are renewed every morning,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.3.4</note> muſt needes much more mooue him to accompliſh the good pleaſure of his will in vs,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.1.</note> who nowe are made the children of his loue in Chriſt. <hi>Therefore neede we not to feare what man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.38. and 39.</note> 
               <hi>yea what Deuills can doe to vs: For neither death, nor life, nor Angells nor principalities, nor powers, nor things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhalbe able to ſeperate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> For our God is full of compaſſion and mercie,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.8. &amp;c.</note> ſlow to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and of great kindnes. Therefore he will
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177173:17"/>not alwayes chyde,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.6.</note> nor keepe his anger for euer: neither will hee deale with vs after our ſinnes, nor reward vs according to our iniquities, ſeeing he pitied vs, and had mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on vs, when we were his enemies. For that mercie that mooued God to beget vs to the hope of lyfe, when we were ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from him, &amp; without hope, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, much more ſhall it mooue him to bring vs (now being made his children) to the enioying of that bleſſed hope. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it followeth, That Gods mercie is the only ground of ſolide and perfect comfort to man, and only ſure ſtay to the ſoule of him that is in trouble: &amp; that contrariwiſe they can haue no ſtedfaſt hope, nor perfect ioy through their hope, who build their hope of lyfe, not vpon the mercie of God, but on their owne merite, or merite of any other creature. Therefore is it that in the ſcripture the moſt lamentable and ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cace of the godly is deſcribed to bee, when as the ſence of Gods mercie faileth them: For then doe they crie out: Will God ſhewe noe more fauour?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.8.</note> Is his Mercie cleane gone for euer? Doth his promiſe faile for euermore? Hath God forgotten to be mercifull? Hath he ſhutt vp his tender mercies in diſpleaſure? This is my death ſayeth the ſeruant of God. Hereby decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that mercie is their only comfort, and cauſe of their lyfe. And where mercie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to be ſhutt vp in diſpleaſure, there is no aſſurance of lyfe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.3.</note> but the ſnares of death doe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe them: then the greeues
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177173:18"/>of the graue doeth gripe them, and they finde trouble and ſorrowe. And then doth their ſoule returne to reſt, when they haue taſted of Gods mercie: and therefore in all their troubles, the ground of their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and drawing neare to God, is, and euer hath bene,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.16.</note> his mercy. Therfore doeth the Apoſtle to the Hebrues will vs to goe bodly to the throne of grace, that we may receaue mercie, and finde grace to helpe in time of neede.</p>
            <p>Now come we to the qualitie of this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that mooueth God to cal vs to the hope of lyfe. The Apoſtle calleth it <hi>his aboundant mercie.</hi> It is moſt certaine, that all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, doe taſte of his mercie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them: yea the very reprobates, and the very Deuils themſelues. For it is a great mercie that they are referued ſo long vnto the iudgement of the great day, and that they and the wicked are ſo long ſpared, vncaſt in hell fyre.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ud. 6.</note> Many a time doth both the word of God, and daylie experience teach vs, that God doth giue many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and deliuerances to the wicked. <hi>Achab</hi> being a man (as witneſſed the booke of God) who had not his like: who did ſell himſelfe to worke wickednes in the ſight of the Lord, hauing heard the threatning of the Prophete againſt him for the killing of Naboth, &amp;c. and humbling himſelfe (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit without true repentance) the Lord did delay his iudgement all his dayes, and did not execute the euill denunced againſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177173:18"/>him, till his ſonnes dayes, for the Lords mercie is aboue all his workes. Therefore, as wee haue ſaid before, hee maketh the Sunne to ariſe on the wicked, &amp; the good, and ſendeth raine to the iuſt and vniuſt. Moreouer, he giueth to the wicked king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Empires, &amp; Dominions, yet doeth not this mercy that obtaines ſo many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, procure to the wicked, that they ſhould be renewed to the hope of Eternall lyfe, and receiue remiſſion of ſinnes. For it is not a ſmall mercie that mooveth God to doe ſo, that is, to iuſtifie a ſinner: to call his enemies to the dignitie of the ſonnes of God, &amp; to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hope of eternal life: it muſt be a mercie running ouer, &amp; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aboundant, that muſt mooue the Lord to beſtow theſe bleſſings which are of greater value, then all the kingdomes of the world. Therefore doth the Apoſtle to the Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans call this grace, a ritch grace: Whereby the Lord hath bene aboundant towards vs in all wiſedome and vnderſtanding.
<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And this aboundance of Gods mercy and grace is moſt clearly manifeſted by that which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh to the Romanes, in declaring both the end of the giuing of the Lawe, and effectes of the Lawe giuen, the end of it (ſayeth he) was, that the offence ſhould abound: whereby it might ſeeme, that thereby wee ſhould bee put further from the hope of grace then before, but hee addeth for our comfort: that where ſinne abounded, there did grace abound
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177173:19"/>much more, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace might raigne through righteouſnes vnto life eternal through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord, even there wher ſinne had raigned vnto death, Before ſin hauing taken occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Law to worke in vs al maner of concupiſcence, that ſinne might appeare ſinne, &amp; to be out of meaſure ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in working death in vs by that which is good: And all this for no other thing, but for the praiſe of the glory of his rich grace, whereby hee doeth abound towardes vs aboue all abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſinne in vs, that his mercie may be knowen to be greater, then our iniquities, yea to be greater then al his workes. For it is ſaide in the 108, Pſalm. <hi>His mercie is great aboue the heauens.</hi> And again: <hi>As high as the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is aboue the earth, ſo great is his mercie towards them that feare him.</hi> For it is not that common goodnes and general mercie of God to all his Creatures, whereby he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth life and being, and moouing to all, &amp; whereby he giveth riches and honours and Kingdomes, that mooveth the Lord to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow this bleſſing of remiſſion of ſinnes, &amp; hope of eternal life. This teacheth vs neuer to content our ſelues with that ſence of Gods mercie, which ariſeth only vpon the enioying of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall bleſſings, be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo great, though he ſhould giue vs the whole world: For this errour doth deceyve many, who thinke the man to bee beloued of God, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he dealeth mercifully in things belonging to this lyfe. Albeit it bee true, that a man may be made Monarch of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177173:19"/>the whole world, and yet bee voyde of the ſauing grace and mercie of God. The true reioycing in Gods mercy ariſeth vpon the hope of the glory of God, builded vpon the peace which we haue toward God through Ieſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.2. and 11.</note> ariſing vpon the remiſſion of ſinns in his bloud, or iuſtification by faith, and the attonement which we haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Therefore,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.6. and 8.</note> gett what we will get from God, wee never ſhall be ſatiſfied with all the tokens of his love and mercy, vntill wee gett that gift of God, whereof Chriſt ſpeaketh in the 4. of Iohn, to the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> when ſhee did denye him a cup of water.
<note place="margin">Iohn 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>If</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>thou kneweſt, that gift of God:</hi> meaning himſelf: &amp; ſhewing vs that he knoweth nothing of the ſauing mercie of God, nor of the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, or warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of eternall lyfe, though he know al the giftes that euer God did giue to man, who yet knoweth not the Lord Ieſus, and hath not bene a feeling partaker of the mercy of God which is in him, &amp; through him. This ſerueth to moove vs to eſteeme more of the ſpirituall bleſſings of God, then of all earthly things.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.6.7.</note> And with <hi>Dauid</hi> to deſire the Lord <hi>to lift vp the light of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cance on vs,</hi> and not with the world to ſeeke for earthly things, <hi>for therby ſhall we haue more ioy of heart, then they haue, when their wheate and their wine doeth abound.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The vſes of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe of this poynt is threefolde: It ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for Inſtruction, for conſolation, &amp; for conviction. For inſtruction in teaching vs,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177173:20"/>ſeeing it is an abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mercy, wherby the Lord doth call vs to the hope of lyfe, and to this effect begetteth vs to bee his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: that ſinne &amp; iniquitie is a thing moſt deteſtable before God, ſince that generall goodnes of God that mooueth him to giue all earthly things to man, maketh him not to giue remiſſion of ſinnes to man: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould wee aboue all things abhorre ſinne, &amp; by all meanes indeuour to eſchew ſinne, as the thing moſt daungerous and pernitious to man. For although thou be a ſinner, God will bleſſe thee with honour and riches of this lyfe, yet will giue thee no portion of his inheritance in the heavens. He promiſed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> when hee prayed that <hi>Iſmaell</hi> might live in his ſight,
<note place="margin">Gene. 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that hee would bleſſe him, and make him fruitfull, and multiplie him exceedingly, that hee ſhould begett 12. Princes, and bee made a great Nation, but his couenant would hee not eſtabliſh with him but with <hi>Iſaac.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought we to beware of this common error of the wordlie, who do eſteeme ſo little of ſinne, that when they ſo licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie doe commit all vncleanes, yet doe they thinke thimſelues in no perill at all, there is, and hath bene euer in the world, ſinne, &amp; prophane perſons, who haue deceiued others with vaine wordes, as though the wrath of God ſhould not come vpon men for whoredom, couetouſnes, &amp;c. Therfore doth the Apoſtle to the Epheſians warne vs: <hi>That we let no man deceyue vs with vaine words.</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:177173:20"/>For, <hi>for ſuch things</hi> (ſayeth the Apoſtle) <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the wrath of God vpon the children of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> Let vs therefore learne not to extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate ſinne, nor ſecurelie to giue our ſelves to ſinne, ſince no common mercie, but an ſuperabundant mercie can obtaine remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinne at the hands of our God. This poynt ſerueth next for conſolation to all penitent ſinners, how wearie and loaden ſoeuer they be: ſince ſinne can not abound in ſo great meaſure, but the mercie of God aboundeth much more: yea this is the very cuſtome of God, that where he maketh the ſence and ſight of ſinne to abound, there he maketh alſo the ſence of his mercie and grace to abound much more. Let vs not therfore with Cain eſteeme our ſinne grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then we can beare and diſtruſt in the mercies of God, ſeeing the Lord himſelfe made vs this promiſe by the Prophet Eſai:
<note place="margin">Eſai. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>Though your ſinnes were as crimſin, they ſhalbe made white as the ſnow: Though they were redd as ſcarlet, they ſhalbe white as wooll.</hi> Therefore is it that God hath ſhewed mercie to the chiefeſt ſinners, that we ſhould not diſpair in Gods mercies, though our iniquities were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great. This doeth the Apoſtle Paule plainely teach vs by his owne example in the firſt cha. to Tim.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.16</note> ſhewing that albeit he was chief of ſinners: &amp; albeit he was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutour, yet was he receyved to mercie, by the exceeding aboundance of the grace of God towards him in Chriſt Ieſus. And that for this cauſe, that Chriſt Ieſus ſhould firſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177173:21"/>ſhew on him all long ſuffering, to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of all them, which in time to come ſhould beleeue in him vnto eternall lyfe. And therefore declareth that this is a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both true and by all meanes worthie to be receyued, to wit, <hi>that Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to ſaue ſinners.</hi> Let not then the haynouſnes of our iniquities dryue vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from God: who is able to remooue our ſinnes from vs as farre as is the Eaſt from the Weſt.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.12.</note> Seeing Chriſt doth call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on al that are wearie and loaden, and doth promiſe them relaxation and caſe:
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> &amp; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth: <hi>That hee did come into the world, not to call the righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 106.4.6. and 45.</note> 
               <hi>but ſinners to repentance:</hi> but let vs rather with the Pſalmiſt praye, <hi>that the Lord will remember vs with the fauour of his people, and viſit vs with his ſaluation, that wee may ſee the felicitie of his choſen, and reioyce in the ioy of his people, and glorie with his inheritance.</hi> For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we haue ſinned with our Fathers, &amp; haue committed iniquitie, and done wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedlie, yet ſhall hee remember his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and call backe his wrath, according to the multitude of his mercies. Thirdly, this poynt ſerueth for conuiction of all who doe eſteeme that it behooueth that their merites bee added to Gods mercies, for obtayning of eternall lyfe: as though the mercy of God were not ſufficient alone to mooue God to graunt vs this benefite. For <hi>if grace doth abound, much more there where ſin hath abounded,</hi> then needeth there nothing to be added to grace, ſince the meaſure of Gods mercy give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in Chriſt, doth alwayes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177173:21"/>exceed the meaſure of our ſinne. Therfore doth the Apoſtle reaſon to the Romanes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance of the grace of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.15.16. &amp; 17.</note> &amp; proveth the certaintie of eternall life by compariſon in this ſimilitude betwixt the grace or gift of God in Chriſt, &amp; the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>Adam</hi> in three reſpects. Firſt, in reſpect of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, &amp; Chriſtes righteouſnes, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. For the Apoſtle ſayeth, that the gift is not ſo as is the offence, &amp; he ſheweth the reaſon, (for ſayeth he): If through the offence of that one, many bee dead: Much more the grace of God &amp; the gift by grace which is by one man Ieſus Chriſt, hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto many: Hereby declaring that the righteouſnes of Chriſt give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs by grace, is more aboundantly beſtowed vpon vs to life, then <hi>Adams</hi> offence was of power vnto death. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, inreſpect of that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, there are two cauſes, to witt, guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, that cometh throgh that one offence of <hi>Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that cometh of Chriſts onely righteouſnes. Neither (ſayeth hee) is the gift ſo, as that which entred by one that ſinned: And he addeth the reaſon. <hi>For</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>the fault came of one offence to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but the gift is of many offences to iuſtification: ſhewing that iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Chriſt, is farre more large then the cauſe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation in Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Seeing that not only that one ſinne, which alone hath brought co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation on all men, but al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our ſinnes are forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt: &amp; ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift of grace abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth much more, &amp; is of greater meaſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the guiltnes of the ſin, that was the cauſe of all mens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177173:22"/>Thirdlie, the Apoſtle reaſoneth from the difference of power betwixt the death that followeth vpon the guiltines of Adams ſinne, &amp; the lyfe that is given to them that are iuſtified by the righteouſnes or obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Chriſt Ieſus. For (ſayeth he) If by one offence death raigned through one, much more ſhall they which receyue that aboundance of grace: and of that gift of it, Righteouſnes raigne in life through one, that is, Ieſus Chriſt. The reaſon is implyed in this ſentence take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the aboundance of grace, and of the gift of that righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. By al which the Apoſtle will aſſure our heartes, that we, who are partakers of the grace &amp; mercie of God in Chriſt, ſhalbe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; that in reſpect. Neither is Adams ſin ſo powerfull to make guiltie vnto death, as the righteouſnes of Chriſtes to iuſtifie vnto lyfe: neither is the guiltines coming from Adams only ſinne, ſo aboundant, as the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification which is by Chriſt only Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: ſeeing our guiltines cometh from one finne, but our iuſtification is not only from that ſinne and guiltines comming from that ſinne but from all ſinnes and guiltines of them all: Neither is death which follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon the guiltines of that one ſinne of Adams vpon all men, of ſuch force to raigne, as the lyfe that commeth to all them that are iuſtified by that one obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Chriſt Ieſus: ſeeing the cauſes of that lyfe are more aboundant, then the cauſes of that death, &amp; therefore th'effect,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177173:22"/>that is the lyfe, muſt be more aboundant or powerful in raigning: Hereby is it euident, that they haue never truely taſted of the ſauing mercie of God in Chriſt, who doe ſo thinke of it as if it were not alone, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out adding ſomething of our merite, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to bring vs to lyfe. Let vs therefore magnifie the mercie of God, which is ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant, plentifull, and running ouer, that it giueth full contentement to the heart, &amp; perfite peace to the ſoule of man: and let vs pray for our ſelves, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle prayeth for the Epheſians,
<note place="margin">Ephe 3.18. and 19.</note> 
               <hi>that being roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and grounded in loue, wee may be able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende with all Saintes what is the bredth, and length, and depth, and height, and to know the love of Ieſus Chriſt, which paſſeth knowledge, that we may be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with all fulnes of God, and ſo haue our ſoules ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with his goodnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now followeth the third poynt,
<note place="margin">The meanes whereby wee are brought to hope.</note> which is concerning the meane or fitting midds whereby the Lord bringeth vs to this ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſed hope, and that is our Regeneration, or newe birth. For as Chriſt ſayeth to Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus: <hi>Except a man bee borne againe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>he can not ſee the kingdome of God,</hi> and conſequentlie can haue no hope of it: therefore ſayeth the Apoſtle here, <hi>that God hath begotten vs againe to hope.</hi> Here haue we to conſider two things. Firſt, what this begetting is. And ſecondly, why it is called <hi>our begetting againe, or ſecond birth.</hi> Which wordes haue a manifeſt relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a former begetting and birth. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the birth, it is fully deſcribed to vs in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177173:23"/>the word of God.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in this ſame chapter of this epiſtle, and 23. verſe, doth ſhew vs the ſence of this conception and birth: both what kinde it is of, and which it is. As for the kinde, he telleth vs, it is not mortall, and ſo periſhing as all fleſh is, but immortall, which liueth and endureth for ever. And that he declareth to bee the word of God, which was preached by the Apoſtle to the world. Secondly, touching the mother, who muſt beare vs, in whoſe wombe this ſeed is ſowen, and out of whoſe bowelles we muſt proceed: the Apoſtle to the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> ſpeaketh plainlie,
<note place="margin">Galat. 4.26</note> ſaying, It is <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> which is aboue, or heauenlie Ieruſalem, that is the true Church of God. whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie is: That ſhe is free, and ſhee ſayeth, the Apoſtle is the Mother of vs all, and was figured by <hi>Sara,</hi> the free woman, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the heire and childe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Thirdly, the Euangeliſt Iohn telleth vs who is the Father, by whom wee muſt be begotten.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.13.</note> &amp; borne againe, <hi>not of blood, nor the will of fleſh, nor the will of man, but God only.</hi> The firſt teacheth vs, to eſteeme much of the bleſſed worde of God, ſince without it, there is no Regeneration, and ſo no hope of lyfe. That there is no Renovation but by the word, it is plaine by the ſpeach of Chriſt him ſelfe in the 17. chapter of Iohn; verſe 17. <hi>Sanctifie them with the trueth: thy word is trueth.</hi> And that without Regeneration, there is no hope, it is manifeſt both by the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177173:23"/>Apoſtle &amp; by the ſpeach aforſaid of Chriſt to <hi>Nicodemus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And by the Apoſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues, where he ſayeth, <hi>that without holines, no man ſhall ſee God.</hi> Therefore ſhould we al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour <hi>to haue the word of God abyding in vs, and dwelling in vs plenteouſlie,</hi> according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation of the Apoſtle to the Coloſſians. And as the Apoſtle ſayth in the next chap. We ſhould as newe borne babes,
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>deſire that ſincere milke of the worde, that we may growe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</hi> For as witneſſeth the Apoſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues: we can not eſcape, if wee neglect ſo great a ſaluation, which at the firſt began to be preached by the Lord, and afterwards was confirmed to vs by them that heard him:
<note place="margin">Hebr. 2.3.</note> ſeeing the word ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Angells was ſtedfaſt, &amp; euery tranſgreſſion &amp; diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, receiued a iuſt reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence or reward. And the Apoſtle in the 2. epiſ.
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.8.</note> to the Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalon. teacheth vs, <hi>that Ieſus Chriſt at his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſhal re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to al that obey not the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond point teacheth vs, not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake nor neglect (as ſayeth the Apoſtle to the Hebr. <hi>our mutuall gatherings together,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.25</note> or <hi>the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip that wee have among our ſelves,</hi> But with <hi>Dauid:</hi> Let vs deſire &amp; require euen this one thing of the Lord: <hi>That we may dwell in the houſe of the Lord al the dayes of our life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.4</note> 
               <hi>to behold the beautie of the Lord, and to viſite his Temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 36.8.</note> 
               <hi>and that we may be ſatiſfied with the fatnes of his houſe, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyve drinke out of the Riuers of his pleaſures.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 46.4.</note> For ther is a Riuer which maketh glad the city of God, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sanctuary of the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the High. For this heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:177173:24"/>is faire in ſituation,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 48.1.2 and 3.</note> the ioy of the whole earth, and Cittie of the great King: In the Palaces whereof, God is knowne for a refuge:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 53. and 6.</note> and out of Zion commeth ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therfore doe the Tribes of the Lord goe vp to Ieruſalem, according to the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Iſraell, to prayſe the Name of the Lord. For there are Thrones ſet for Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.</note> euen the Thrones of the houſe of Dauid: And therfore ſeing this is the place of ſafetie and ſaluation, where the beautie of the Lord is to be ſeene, where the voyce of the Lord is to be heard from his holy O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, we ſhould reioyce with <hi>Dauid,</hi> when we heare the people ſay:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.</note> 
               <hi>We will goe vp into the houſe of the Lord. Our feet ſhall ſtand in the gates of Ieruſalem.</hi> For as witneſſeth Dauid: Bleſſed are they that dwell in the houſe of the Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.</note> for they ſhall euer praiſe him: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did his ſoule long and fainte for the Courtes of the Lordes houſe: yea his ſoule panted after the Lord, as the hart after the waters, being baniſhed from the publicke worſhip of God by the perſecution of <hi>Saul;</hi> and his heart was poured out, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred that he had gone with the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and led them in the houſe of God with the voyce of ſinging and prayſe, as a multitude that keepeth a feaſt:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.11.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe a day in the Courtes of the Lord, is better then a thouſand other where: and better is it to be a doore keeper in the houſe of the Lord, then to dwell in the tabernacles of wickednes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 87.</note> 
               <hi>for glorious things are ſpoken of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our God.</hi> For of Zio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſaid, that many
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177173:24"/>are borne in her. Seeing therefore that our ſpirituall birth is in heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> where the ſeed of Gods worde is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſowen.
<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> For which cauſe the kingdome of heauen is likened to a ſower that went foorth to ſowe his ſeed: Hither ſhould we reſort, for God is in the middes of her. But let vs remember that it is Ieruſalem that is aboue, and which is free, which is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vs all, as ſayeth the Apoſtle. For <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> who was borne of the bound woman <hi>Hagar,</hi> who was the type of earthlie Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, was not the heire, but Iſaac, who was borne of <hi>Sara</hi> the free woman, who was the type of the heauenly Ieruſalem, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all the children of God. He was the heire, that is, they who are the children of the Law, and doe remaine in the bondage thereof, are not truely borne of God to the hope of lyfe, but they who are begotten by the Goſpell in the boſome of the Church, ſet at libertie, and walking in the libertie, wherewith Chriſt hath made vs free,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.1.</note> they are truly begotten of God to this bleſſed hope, becauſe they are after the maner of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> children of the promiſe,
<note place="margin">Gal. 42.3.</note> whereas the other are borne after the fleſh.</p>
            <p>The third poynt touching the Lord, who begetteth vs to this hope, doth teach vs what ſort of generation it is, that maketh vs to haue this hope, to wit, a ſpirituall, and no fleſhlie birth. For as Chriſt ſayeth to <hi>Nicodemus</hi> in the third of Iohn: <hi>That which is borne of the fleſh, is fleſh: and that which is borne of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:177173:25"/>the ſpirit, is ſpirit.</hi> And it is playne by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to the Corinthians:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> 
               <hi>That fleſh and blood can not inherite the kingdome ef God.</hi> Therefore is it neceſſary, <hi>that we be borne</hi> (as ſayeth our Sauiour in the third of Iohn) <hi>by water and of the ſpirit,</hi> that is of the ſpirit of God: who is of the ſame force and nature ſpirituall to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſoule, touching the ſpirituall filth of ſinne, that water is toward the body in bodily filth in waſhing and purging of it. Therefore alſo is the ſame ſpirit in the 4. of Eſay called the ſpirit of burning, becauſe as fire to gold, ſo the ſpirit to vs, doeth effectually purge the droſſe of ſinne. For this cauſe is it alſo that Iohn the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt ſayeth,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>That Christ ſhall baptize vs with the holy ſpirit and fire:</hi> for we muſt be the children of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> before we can be his heirs, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the Apoſtle, both to the Romanes and Galathians. Therefore doth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle here giue thanks to God,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4 7.</note> euen for this, <hi>that he hath begetten vs,</hi> and ſo hath made vs his children, that we may haue hope to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite his kingdome. The vſe hereof is, to learne, that it is the greateſt dignitie, and higheſt prerogatiue that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> attaine too, to be made the children of God. Therfore doth <hi>Iohn</hi> call this <hi>a gift of power,</hi> in the firſt of his Goſpell, ſaying to thoſe that recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him, he gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this power to be the ſonnes of God. And in the third Chapter of his firſt Epiſtle, he eſteemeth it the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Gods greateſt love to man, ſaying: Beholde brethren, howe great a love the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:177173:25"/>Father hath given vs, that we ſhould bee called the ſonnes of God. We haue next to conſider, that this birth muſt bee after a former birth, becauſe it is ſaid, that <hi>God hath begotten vs againe.</hi> And Chriſt to <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> ſaith plainelie, <hi>that he that is not borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, can not ſee the kingdome of God.</hi> For our firſt birth neither maketh vs the children of God: neither putteth vs in hope of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. Wee may well be the children of Kings, of great Lords, and Princes, and ſo haue hope of their inheritance by our firſt birth, but though an Emperour haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten thee, it maketh thee not the ſonne of God, nor heire of his kingdome. And though a begger have begotten thee, thou art no farther from the kingdom of God, then he that is borne of a king: ſeeing the firſt birth helpeth nothing to this prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue, but it is the ſecond birth that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it. The eſtate of man, be he what hee will, Iewe or Gentile, great or ſmall, poore or riche, noble or ignoble in his firſt birth, which is declared by the Apoſtle to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians, to wit,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>that he is the child of wrath by nature:</hi> &amp; therefore can haue no hope but of wrath. For as David confeſſeth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, it is true of all fleſh: Beholde <hi>I was borne in iniquitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5. Rom. 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>and in ſinne hath my mother con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyved me: and the wages of ſinne</hi> (ſayeth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>is death:</hi> this is the inheritance that cometh to vs by our earthly and naturall Parentes, of what degree, dignity, or eſtate ſoeuer they be in this world. The vſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177173:26"/>of is twofolde.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it ſerveth to beate downe the pride of al fleſh, &amp; to teach men not to glorie in their bloud, nor kinred: ſeeing it is not by bloud, nor by the will of man, nor by the will of fleſh that we are borne the children of God. For though a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might reckon to Abraham, as did the Scribes &amp; Phariſees in the 8. of Iohn, as to their Father in the fleſh, yet may hee be ſtill the childe of the Devill, as witneſſeth Chriſt of them ſelves in that ſame place. For as the Apoſtle ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: <hi>They are not all Iſraell that are of Iſraell: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they all children, that are of the ſeed of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi> Yea though a man might reckon his kinred to Adam, yet hath he not wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to glorie: ſeeing (as ſayeth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Romanes</hi>) <hi>by that one Man ſinne entred into the world, and by ſinne death,</hi> and not only entted, but by his only ſinne, all are made ſinners, &amp; death went over all men. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs learne the leſſon which <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> teacheth the Phariſees and Saddu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cees in the Goſpell according to Matthew: <hi>Let vs not thinke to ſay with our ſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>We haue A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham to our Father: For God is able of ſtones to raiſe vp children to Abraham:</hi> but rather with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Philippians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and put no confidence in the fleſh, although we had all matter of glorying in the fleſh that ever man had. Let vs learn with the Apoſtle in that place <hi>To esteeme all fleſhly prerogative to bee loſſe: yea to be dunge, for Chriſles ſake, that we may gaine him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:177173:26"/>
            <p> The ſecond vſe hereof is, to teach vs, that there can be no hope of life in a man, who is not Regenerate by God, and begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of him againe: ſeeing this is the meane by which the the Lord bringeth vs to this hope: and therefore the boaſting of the wicked, that they hope to goe to heauen, is nothing but vanitie: and all the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence they haue, is nothing els but a vaine and deceitfull thought of a blinde &amp; foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh braine: thinking they ſhall goe to heaven, becauſe Chriſt dyed for ſinners, not remembring that all who are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his death, muſt needes be renewed in the ſpirit of their minde to the Image of God: and muſt finde themſelves caſt in a new moulde, and faſhioned to another ſhape, and borne over againe. Therefore we ſhould diligently trye our ſelves, and conſider if God at any time hath bin ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall in vs to the alteration of the ſpirit of our minde, &amp; renovation of our ſoules: and if his ſpirit doth poſſeſſe and lead vs ſo, that our converſation be after the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and not after the fleſh. And as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Peter in his ſecond epiſtle, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs,
<note place="margin">2. Pet 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Wee ſhould ſtudie to make our calling and election ſure, by adding to our faith, vertue,</hi> and ſo foorth. For they can haue no certaintie of their calling, that are not ſanctified, and therefore no aſſured hope. For when God maketh vs his ſonnes,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> he ſendeth the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his ſon in our heartes, which cryeth,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>Abba, Father,</hi> For if any have not the ſpirit
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177173:27"/>of Chriſt, he is not his, ſayeth the Apoſtle to the Romanes.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.10</note> 
               <hi>And if the ſpirit of Chriſt be in vs</hi> (ſayeth the ſame Apoſtle) <hi>the ſame body is dead, becauſe of ſinne:</hi> the ſpirit is lyfe becauſe of Righteouſnes. Therefore we may iuſtly conclude with the Apoſtle Pieter in the firſt chapter aforſaid of his ſecond epiſtle, after hee hath exhorted vs <hi>to ioyne vertue to our faith, and to vertue knowledge, &amp; to knowledge temperance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.9.</note> and ſo foorth: that whoſoever hath not theſe things, hee is blinde and ſeeth not farr off, and hath forgotten that he was waſhed from his olde ſinnes, and ſo conſequently, that their hope is but a blinde hope: their confidence, a blinde confidence: their boaſting, a blinde boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.
<note place="margin">2 Co. 5.17</note> 
               <hi>For if any man be in Christ Ieſus, he is a new creature,</hi> ſayeth the Apoſtle to the <hi>Corinthes.</hi> So to conclude this point, it were better to a man never to have bene borne in this worlde, then after he is borne, not to bee borne over againe by God: And woe is the man, who before the laying downe of this naturall life, hath not obtayned ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the fourth point,
<note place="margin">Hope fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> which is the benefite it ſelfe, vnto the which God of his mercie doth beget vs againe: that is, a living, or lively hope, or hope of lyfe. This ſheweth vs the purpoſe of God in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting vs, which is to cauſe vs hope. For as we have ſaid before: Firſt, wee muſt bee made the children of God, before we can hope to enioy his inheritance. Therefore
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177173:27"/>our Regeneration is a warning to vs, that wee are the heires of God, and coheires with Chriſt, and obligeth vs to hope for the glorie of God, ſeeing God hath begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vs: <hi>Becauſe</hi> (as ſaith the Apoſtle here) <hi>he begetteth vs to hope,</hi> therefore where hope is not, there is no new birth, for the Lord can not bee fruſtrate of the ende of his worke: for hee that renewes vs vnto hope with renovation gives hope: Therefore the ſanctified man in Chriſt, may be ſure of glorie, and lyfe everlaſting, according as the Apoſtle ſheweth vs: <hi>Whom he calleth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note> 
               <hi>hee iustifienh: and whom hee iuſtifieth, him hee glorifieth.</hi> In this benefite wee have two things to conſider. Firſt, what is the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, tot wit, hope. Next, what is meant by the propertie of this hope, in that it is called, <hi>a lively hope.</hi> Concerning the firiſt, the Apoſtle deſcribing our eſtate before the Lord doe beget vs, and make vs parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the adoption, doth declare, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt of our miſeries, this was one, that we had no hope. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to vs the mercy of God in our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and regeneration, ſhewing that we are his workma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhip created in Chriſt Ieſus vnto good workes, which God had orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that we ſhould walke in them being iuſtified by faith, he willeth vs to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what we were before, ſaying: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that ye beeing in time paſt Gentiles in the fleſh, &amp; called vncircumciſion of them which are called circumciſion in the fleſh,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:177173:28"/>made with handes, that yee were, I ſay, at that time without Chriſt, &amp; were aliaunts from the common wealth of Iſrael, and were ſtrangers from the couenants of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and had no hope, and were without God in the world. This is the miſerable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of vs all, before wee be called of God to the adoption of his ſonnes, and be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of him againe, wee are all without Chriſt, without hope, and without God in the world. What greater miſerie can there be,
<note place="margin">Act. 17.28.</note> then have a being, and yet without him, in whom wee have <hi>our being, our lyfe, our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and all things,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſayeth in the Actes: And knowing that we muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from this life, to have no hope of lyfe thereafter. Miſerable indeed is our eſtate by nature, how much ſoever we glorie in it, ſo much the more miſerable: that wee have neither ſenſe nor ſorrow of this our miſerie. Who is he that can reioyce in any thing, while hee abydeth without him, in whom are all things? And howe can the heart ſufficiently praiſe, love and magnifie the Lord, when it taſted of this his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in begetting vs againe? And ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, taking from vs all our miſeries, &amp; making vs bleſſed in giving vs hope, and himſelfe to bee our God and Father in Chriſt: through whom (ſayeth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Epheſians) we both,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.18.19. and 22</note> that is Iewe and Gentill, <hi>haue one entrance vnto the Father by one ſpirit, and are no more ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers &amp; forreners, but citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:177173:28"/>God, and in whom wee are build together to bee the habitation of God by the ſpirit.</hi> It is not without good reaſon, that the Apoſtle here in this place can not ſpeake of this mercie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bleſſing him, who hath brought vs to this bleſſed eſtate of hope. And great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter have we of reioycing who have taſted of the like mercie, If wee conſider that which the Apoſtle ſaith to the Romanes, <hi>That wee are ſaved by hope.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.24.</note> For as he ſaith in another Epiſtle: <hi>We walke here by faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>and not by ſight,</hi> and therfore taking from vs hope, our ſalvation and lyfe is taken from vs, which wee doe poſſeſſe by hope: for this is the difference of faith and hope, that by faith we beleeue the promiſes of ſalvation in Chriſt, which <hi>hope</hi> waiteth for: ſo that faith hath reſpect to lyfe and ſalvation, as it is embraced by vs here in this world: Hope, hath relation to them as wee ſhall poſſeſſe them in the world to come, ſo that hope doeth alwayes follow faith, &amp; han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vpon it, although they be often times take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſcripture the one for the other indifferently: The one looketh to lyfe, &amp; apprehendeth it promiſed in the world, the other wayteth for the revelation of it from heaven, as it is poſſeſſed by Chriſt at the right hande of the Father. This is now the bleſſing vnto the which the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth vs againe, ſo that without Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration we are hopeles, and ſo without happines, &amp; being borne againe. Wee may have faith and hope in God, according as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:177173:29"/>ſaith this ſame Apoſtle in this ſame Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21.22.</note> when hee declareth who they are for whom Chriſt was both ordayned before the foundation of the world, and alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the laſt times. For your ſake ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>which by his meanes doe beleeve in God that rayſed him from the dead, and gave him glorie, that your faith and hope might bee in God: having purified your ſoules in obeying the trueth, through the ſpirit:</hi> (&amp; further) <hi>being borne a new, not of mortall ſeed, but of immortall by the word of God.</hi> Whereby it is plaine, that as Chriſt is ſend into the world for none but ſuch as doe beleeve in God by his meanes, ſo none can have any faith or hope but they, who have their ſoules purified &amp; borne a new.</p>
            <p>The propertie of this hope is,
<note place="margin">The nature of true hope</note> that it is <hi>livelie,</hi> or <hi>living,</hi> and it is ſo called for three reſpectes. Firſt, becauſe of the livelie wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that is in it. For all the ſpirituall gifts of God which he beſtoweth in Chriſt, are livelie, as hee himſelfe is lyfe: And this the Saints do finde in themſelves, that the faith of Ieſus is a livelie faith: their love is a livelie love, &amp; their hope, a livelie hope. For theſe graces doe not lye dead in the ſoule where they are, but by their livelie operation and working, doe make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves manifeſt. Therefore the Apoſtle to the Theſſalonians, ſpeaking of their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, deſcribeth them from their lively and effectuall properties: <hi>Remembring</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>your effectuall faith, your diligent love, and your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient hope in the Lord Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.2</note> Therefore that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177173:29"/>faith, that hope, that love, that lyeth dead in them who profeſſe them, are no faith, no hope, no love at all. And ſo iuſtly doeth S. Iames diſpute againſt that faith that hath no workes, as a dead faith: whereas the faith, the hope, the love that God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the heart, are all livelie, as procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from him who is life it ſelfe. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reſpect whereof it is called <hi>livelie,</hi> is, becauſe as it hath life in it ſelfe, ſo giveth it lyfe to the ſoule in which it is, and maketh the ſoule which was dead in ſinne &amp; treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe before, now to live in Chriſt, and in him to bring forth the fruits of life. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayeth Iohn in the third Chapter of his 1, epiſtle 3. and 5. <hi>That whoſoever hath this hope, purgeth himſelfe, as he is pure.</hi> For this is the nature of their ſpirituall bleſſings, that they themſelves have lyfe in them: and doth quicken the ſoule in which they are. For God exerciſeth his ſaving power by them in the hearts of his Saintes. Therfore ſaith the Apoſtle hereafter,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>That we are kept by the power of God through faith.</hi> And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Paul to the Coloſſians, doth ſay:
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.12</note> 
               <hi>That we are raiſed againe from the dead in Chriſt, by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall working of God, or by the faith of God which worketh mightilie,</hi> ſo that we may iuſtly ſaye, that as the faith is dead, which hath no working, ſo hee alſo is yet without faith, who albeit hee profeſſeth faith, yet is not quickned to the lyfe of God thereby: for even in this life by faith and hope wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to live that life, which ſhalbe made perfite in vs in the world to come.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:177173:30"/>
            <p> The third reſpect is, becauſe that eternall life and glory which as yet is not manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, but is referved in the heavens to the appearing of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, is nowe poſſeſſed by hope, ſo that we lay hold vpon it, and are made perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of it, albeit as yet not manifeſted. Therefore is it that the Apoſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſaith:
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.24.</note> 
               <hi>That by hope we are ſaved: for no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hopeth for the thing which he ſeeth.</hi> Hereby tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs, that albeit our <hi>lyfe be hidd with Chriſt in God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.3.</note> as ſaieth the Apoſtle to the Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>yet by hope we poſſeſſe it.</hi> According as the Apoſtle to the Epheſians declareth the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the Saints in Chriſt, <hi>by the mightie power of God which is in them,</hi> to wit, <hi>that they are lifted vp with him, and ſett with him at the right hande of the maiestie in the highest places.</hi> As like wiſe the ſame Apoſtle Peter in this ſame chapter, declaring the cauſe why they that beleeue in Chriſt, albeit they ſee him not, doe reioyce with a ioy vnſpeakable and glorious, ſayth. It is becauſe <hi>that they receyue the end of their faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.9.</note> that is, <hi>the ſalvation of their ſoules.</hi> To theſe three we may add the 4. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, why this hope is called livelie, and that is, becauſe in all the tribulations and ſorrowes of this life, it is the onely thing that ſuſtaineth vs, and maketh vs in death it ſelfe, to live and reioyce, knowing what is layed vp for vs in the heavens. For the only thing that maketh the Saints indure patientlie, vea and ioyfully, this troubles which ſwallow vp the wicked, is the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177173:30"/>hope. The Apoſtle to the Hebrues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth this,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.34</note> ſhewing that the cauſe why the Hebrues did ſuſtaine all affliction, and among the reſt, the ſpoiling of their goods with ioy and gladnes, was, becauſe they knew, they had a better and an induring ſubſtance or ritches layde vp for them in the heavens. Therefore doeth the ſame Apoſtle call this hope, the Ancor of the ſoule, and deelareth that they who have their refuge to lay holde vpon this hope, <hi>have ſtrong conſolation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.10.</note> For by this hope wee attayne to the reſurrection from the dead, ſo that death it ſelfe can not ſpoyle them of life, who are renewed to this bleſſed hope. The vſe of al this is, to make vs obey that leſſon which the Apoſtle giveth vs to the Hebru. which is, <hi>to holde fast the profeſſion of our hope, without wavering,</hi> ſeeing therin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth both our life and conſolation, and conſtantlie to awaite for the appearing of it:
<note place="margin">2. Tit. 2.13</note> as the Apoſtle Paul to Titus exhorteth vs, <hi>That we may in patience poſſeſſe our ſoules, and ioyfullie indure all afflictions of this life,</hi> ſince ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hope, we can not be ſpoyled of lyfe.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the laſt point to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in this firſt part touching the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite whervnto we are begotten againe by God:
<note place="margin">The ground whervpon our hope is builded</note> which is the ground and foundation of this hope wherevpon it is builded, which is the Reſurrection of Chriſt from the dead. For, as ſaith the Apoſtle to the Corinthians:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.17.</note> 
               <hi>If Chriſt bee not rayſed from the dead, our faith is vaine, we are yet in our ſinnes.</hi> For
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:177173:31"/>we muſt vnderſtand, firſt, that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of hope co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in the reſurrection from the dead: which being taken from vs, wee are of all men the moſt miſerable. Seeing, as ſaith the Apoſtle to the Corinthians:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 15 No hope without knowledge of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection</note> 
               <hi>If in this life only we have hope in Chriſt, we are of all men the moſt miſerable:</hi> for beſides the croſſes and calamities wherevnto we are ſubiect in this life, death cometh in betwixt vs, &amp; our hope in Chriſt, and it ſeemeth to cutt vs vtterlie from him, &amp; all fruition of his bliſſe. For if death had dominion over vs, ſo that the ſorrowes thereof could not be looſed but that we ſhould be holden of it, what avayled it vs to be in ieopardie eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie houre?
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 19.18.</note> and wherefore ſhould we ſuffer affliction for the name of Ieſus? <hi>for all that ſleepe in him were periſhed,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle in the ſame place to the Corinthians, <hi>If there were no Reſurrection,</hi> Therefore to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs not only againſtal the afflictions of this preſent life, but chieflie againſt that laſt and moſt fearfull tentation of death, the Lord doth inſtruct vs in the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the dead. This was the comfort that <hi>Iob</hi> had in all his miſeries, as he ſaieth himſelf, That although after his skinne, wormes deſtroy his bodie, <hi>yet ſhall I ſee God in my fleſh, whom I my ſelfe ſhall ſee, and my eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, and none other for me, though my reynes are conſumed within me.</hi> This alſo ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Corinthi. was the cauſe which made him not onely to faint,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor 5.1.</note> but alſo to ſighe: <hi>Deſiring to be diſſolved,</hi> even becauſe he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:177173:31"/>did know, <hi>If this earthly houſe of this tabernacle were deſtroyed, he had a building given vs of God, an houſe not made with handes, but eternall in the heavens:</hi> So that death was no terrour at all to him, who did know, that he which rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lord Ieſus, ſhould raiſe him vp al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and give him a glorious bodie. And for this cauſe is it that Chriſt Ieſus in the ſixt chap. of Iohn, willing to confirme his aſſertion, and ſaying: <hi>That of all which the Father had given him, he ſhould looſe nothing.</hi> ſo oft bringeth in this promiſe: <hi>And I will raiſe him vp at the last day.</hi> And with this he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted <hi>Martha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 11.2</note> mourning for the death of her brother <hi>Lazarus,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Thy brother ſhal riſe againe.</hi> And the Apoſtle Paul writing to the Theſſalonians, willing to comfort them, &amp; to ſtay their exceſſiue mourning for the dead, doth bring in this ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>That they which are a ſleepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſhal riſe at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Lord.</hi> This point therefore muſt we carefullie hold, ſince without it we can haue no comfort. And to this effect we haue next to conſider, what it is that doth aſſure vs and certifie our ſoules, that we ſhall riſe againe. For it is a matter harde to be beleeved,
<note place="margin">The aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our reſurrection dependeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt</note> that the body which is once dead &amp; turned into duſt, ſhal raiſe againe. The thing that giveth certaine hope to vs of out reſurrection, is the Reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour. If he had not ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, we could never have had any hope that ever our bodies ſhuld haue received life after death. For this is a ſure grounde, which, we muſt ſtedfaſtlie hold,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:177173:32"/>that our God mindeth to doe nothing to vs which hee hath not firſt done to Ieſus Chriſt our head and Prince of our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for our cauſe. For he is as the firſt fruits in all things:
<note place="margin">Col. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>for in all things he hath the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle to the Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: <hi>therefore alſo is hee the beginning, and firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, among the dead.</hi> And againe, to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, the Apoſtle ſheweth vs <hi>that he is made the first frutes of them that ſleepe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 19.20.</note> Seeing then that in the firſt frutes the whole is ſanctified, &amp; no otherwayes: It muſt needs follow, that Chriſt behooved to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo from the dead, before wee could be raiſed: our reſurrection depending vpon his, &amp; flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from his. For as ſaieth the Apoſtle in that ſame place to the Corinthians:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.21.</note> 
               <hi>As by man came death: ſo alſo by man cometh the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the dead. For as in Adam all dye, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made aliue: but euerie one</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in his owne order: the firſt fruites is Chriſt, thereafter they that are Chriſtes at his appearing.</hi> Therefore doeth he call him ſelfe in the 11.
<note place="margin">Iohn 11.25</note> chapter of Iohn, ſpeaking to Martha, <hi>The Reſurrection and Lyfe.</hi> Herof it followeth, that he who knoweth not Chriſt to be ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from the dead, and beleeveth not that he is riſen, can no wayes beleeve that ever he ſhall riſe againe to life.
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.21.</note> For this ſame Apoſtle Peter in this ſame Chapter, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after plainlie witneſſeth, that <hi>God hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Christ from the dead, and hath giuen him glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that our faith &amp; hope ſhould be in God.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he teacheth vs two things concerning
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:177173:32"/>our hope. Firſt, that it muſt bee in God. Secondlie, that it can not bee in God, but through Chriſt: and therefore that wee could not hope in God that he would raiſe vs from the dead, if he had not firſt raiſed Chriſt our head: ſeeing wee muſt beleeve in God through him. The vſe of this point is twofolde. Firſt, it learneth vs to diſcerne the trueth and veritie of our hope, from the right ground and foundation of it.
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.21</note> For every mans hope muſt have a foundation to vpholde it: even as <hi>our faith and hope is the foundation whereby we are vpholden,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle to the Coloſſians. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the which, if we fall, we fall from God, and from life: ſo our hope hath the ſame foundation, whereby it is vpholden in vs, that wee doe not caſt away our confidence and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of our hope, albeit aſſailed with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable and grievous tentations: this fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation is Chriſt himſelf. And therfore whyle the Apoſtle doth exhort vs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in our hope, and patient running of the race that is layed before vs vnto the end, he willeth vs to looke ſtill vpon Ieſus Chriſt, the authour &amp; finiſher of our faith. For if our ſight be caſt vpon any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him,
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.18.</note> ſo that we drawe our eyes from be holding him, then muſt our hope faile vs. It is ſaid of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Father of the faithfull, who aboue hope, beleeved vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hope, that he ſhould bee the Father of many nations, according to the promiſe, that hee conſidered not his owne body,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:177173:33"/>which nowe was dead, beeing almoſt an hundreth yeares old: neither the deadnes of <hi>Saraes</hi> wombe: neither did he doubt of the promiſe, but did looke to him who did promiſe: being fullie aſſured, that he was able to performe herein this promiſe made to Abraham. If Abraham had not caſt his ſight on him that promiſed, that is the Sonne of God, but had looked to him ſelfe or Sara, he could haue had no hope of the promiſe. So in the promiſe of our Reſurrection fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead to eternall life, if we caſt our eyes vpon our ſelues, &amp; our bodies dying and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuming and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into duſt whereof they were made, we can neuer hope that we can riſe againe vnto life: but looking to Chriſt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>in whom all the promiſes of God are Yea and Amen,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle to the Corinth. we finde ſufficient reaſon and grounde to beleeve the Reſurrection from the dead. Seeing he who was made man like to his brethren in all things, except ſinne, albeit walking in the ſimilitude of ſinfull fleſhe, being put to death, did looſe the ſorrowes of death, and was declared mightilie to be the ſonne of God, touching the ſpirit of ſanctification by the reſutrection from the dead.
<note place="margin">2 Cor 4.14.</note> Therefore doe we with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Corinths, know, That he which hath raiſed vp the Lorde Ieſus, ſhall rayſe vs vp alſo by Ieſus: for therefore is it that we are baptiſed for dead, as ſaieth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to the Corinthes. For wee that are
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177173:33"/>baptiſed into Ieſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.15 29. Rom. 6.3.</note> haue bene bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed into his death, ſaieth the Apoſtle to the Romanes. And therefore if we bee dead with him, we beleeve alſo that wee ſhall live with him. For if we be planted with him to the ſimilitude of his death, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo ſhall we be to the ſimilitude of his reſurrection, ſaith the ſame Apoſtle in the ſame place. For he that is Chriſtes, hath the ſpirit of God dwelling in him, as is plaine by the Apoſtle to the Romanes.
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.5. Rom. 8.8. 1 Iohn 3.24.</note> And Iohn in his firſt Epiſtle ſaieth, That hereby we know that he abydeth in vs, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by that ſpirit which he hath given vs And if the ſpirit of him that raiſed vp Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt from the dead dwell in vs, hee that raiſed vp Chriſt from the death, shall alſo quicken our mortal bodies by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that dwelleth in vs.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> So doeth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle from the preſence of the ſame ſpirit prove the like effect in rayſing vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the death:
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.13.</note> and therfore as he ſaith to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. becauſe we have the ſame ſpirite of faith (as it is written, I beleeved and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue ſpoken) wee alſo beleeve, and therefore ſpeake, <hi>knowing that he which hath raiſed vp the Lord Ieſus, ſhall raiſe vs vp alſo by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and ſet vs with him.</hi> So it is evident, that the Reſurrection of Ieſus from the death, is the ground and foundation of the hope of Reſurrection from the dead to all that have the ſame ſpirit of life that is in Chriſt Ieſus dwelling in them: for the law of that ſpirit of life which is in Chriſt Ieſus, doth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:177173:34"/>free all thoſe in whom he dwelleth, from the law both of ſinne and death,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.2.</note> as teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Apoſtle to the Romanes. Hereby are wee taught two profitable leſſons: the firſt is,
<note place="margin">Al the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God are firſt ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in Chriſt himſelfe.</note> to carefully marke how farre God accompliſhed his promiſes in Chriſt his ſonne. For ſo farre may all that beleeve, be aſſured, that he ſhall accompliſhe them in them through Chriſt. Therefore have we hope of ſanctification from ſinne, Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the dead, and glorification in the heavens, becauſe theſe promiſes are fulfilled in Chriſt, whom we ſee crowned with glorie and honour, as ſayeth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Hebrewes:
<note place="margin">Heb. 2.9.</note> which was made a little inferior to the Angels, through the ſuffering of death. <hi>For God hee predeſtinateth all thoſe whom he hath foreknowen to be made like to the Image of his Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note> 
               <hi>that he might be the firſt born among manie brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And therfor the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt ſhould be to vs moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſince we can know no more, nor hope for no more bleſſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, then we firſt knew to have been beſtowed on Ieſus Chriſt our head,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 30.</note> who is made to vs of God, wiſedome, ſanctification iuſtification and Redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.8. &amp;c</note> Therfore did the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> eſteeme all things loſſe, for the excellent knowledge ſake of Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: and did iudge all things but dung, that hee might gaine Chriſt, and know him: And the vertue of his Reſurrection, that he alſo thereby might attaine to the reſurrection from the dead. The ſecond leſſon is, to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177173:34"/>pray to God day and night, to ſend vs that bleſſed ſpirit of promiſe, ſeeing the things which are wrought in Chriſt, ſhall not bee accompliſhed in any, but thoſe who have the ſame ſpirit of lyfe, that is in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus dwelling in them. And therefore they can not hope for renovation to the Image of God, and reſtauration of their dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to the lyfe of God, and glorification with the glorie of God, wherwith Chriſt is glorified, who have not the ſpirit of Chriſt This is the firſt vſe of this poynt, whereby wee are taught to diſcerne true hope from the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and foundation whereon only it is builded, and that is Ieſus Chriſt alone. The ſecond vſe is, to teach vs,
<note place="margin">A diſtinct knowledge of Chriſt requiſite.</note> not only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedlie to learne Chriſt, but even perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlie to conſider all the degrees and ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall partes of that great worke of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by him for the more ſolide and ſtedfaſt fixing of our hartes in him. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it be moſt true, that he who is perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the death of the Sonne of God, is alſo pertaker of his life &amp; of his glory, &amp;c. yet neither can the faith and hope bee ſo ſtable, nor the comfort ſo great, as when in Chriſt our Lord we ſee a perticular grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and warrant for every article of our faith. Therefore in this place doth the Apoſtle lead vs to the reſurrection of Chriſt from the dead, for eſtabliſhing our hearts in the hope of our life with God in the heavens. For as wee goe forward in conſideration of the partes of Chriſtes working and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:177173:35"/>actions done by him, for our full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, ſo doeth our faith increaſe, &amp; our hope by degree to degree: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we looke to Chriſt dying for vs, we learne to beleeve remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes in his blood: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we goe on to his refurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we imbrace the hope of lyfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead: when we looke to his aſcention, we apprehend our aſcending to the heavens: and in his glorification, wee are comforted by the hope of that ſame glorie. Thus doeth it ſerve much for our comfort, to know all the perticularities of Chriſtes humiliation &amp; exaltation, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the Lord our God hath revealed them in his word, beginning at his Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, going on to his birth in great ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenes, expreſſing therafter the troubles of his youth: laying out next the ſorrowes of his life, whyle hee caried our infirmities: walking in the ſimilitude of ſinfull fleſhe, and ſubiect to all the infirmities thereof, except ſinne: proceeding to his death, and kinde thereof being moſt accurſed,
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the Apoſtle to the Galathians. In all which the ſpirit of God letteth vs ſee our infirmities, our ſinnes, and our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes layed vpon him, and vs acquitted of them in him. Thereafter are we led to his buriall, wherein is ſet before vs the hope of the everlaſting aboliſhing of ſinne. Then come we to his Reſurrection, the ground of our hope once to ſee death, that laſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, aboliſhed and deſtroyed: and ſo we are guided on with him to the heavens in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:177173:35"/>his aſcenſion, and at length to his glorie at the right hand of the Father. This diſtinct faith riſing vpon the diſtinct conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and knowledgd of the diſtinct operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the power of God through Chriſt, in them that beleeve, is lively ſet foorth to vs by the Apoſtle to the Epheſians.
<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.17. &amp;c. &amp; 2.1.</note> Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them that they might receive <hi>the ſpirit of wiſedome and revelation,</hi> to that ſame effect that they might know diſtinctly the parts of his working in them that beleeve, and ſhewing them perticularly certaine of the ſaid effectes of his power: Firſt, their quickning with Chriſt: Secondly, the ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them vp together with Chriſt: and thirdly, the making of them to ſitt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him in the heavenly places in Chriſt Ieſus. And the ſame Apoſtle writing to the Coloſſians, and ſhewing that we are accompliſhed and perfited in him alone, doth manifeſt the ſame by perticular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, in theſe wordes: <hi>In whom</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>yee are etrcumciſed with circumciſion made without handes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2. &amp; 11. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>by putting off the ſinfull bodie of the fleſh, through the circumciſion of Chriſt,</hi> which hee expoundeth thereafter more perticular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in the partes of this circumciſion, and ſeverall groundes of everie part, ſaying, in that ye are buried with him through bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. Secondlie, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yee are alſo raiſed vp together through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, which raiſed him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead. Thirdlie, and you which were dead in ſinne, and in the vncircumciſion of the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:177173:36"/>fleſhe, hath he quickened togither with him, forgiving you al your ſinns. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and putting out the hand-writing that was againſt vs, which was contrarie to vs, he even tooke it out of the way, and faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it on the Croſſe. And fiftlie, he ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Principalities and Powers, &amp; hath made a shewe of them openly, and hath triumphed over them in the ſame Croſſe. Thus doeth the Apoſtle leade vs to the ſight of our death and buriall ſpirituall to ſinne: of our riſing from the dead: of our ſpiritual quickening with the life of God: of the aboliſhing of our debt and dittay: in abrogation of the Law, which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to vs: and of the vtter overthrow of our ſpirituall enemies, and our glorious triumph over them all in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord: which at length our God ſhall fullie accompliſhe in everie one of vs, in the glorious appearing of Ieſus Chriſt our Saviour, whoſe Name be bleſſed for ever. AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:177173:36"/>
            <head>The ſecond Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. Epiſt. of Pet. Cap. 1. verſes.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="4">4. To an inheritance immortall and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, and that withereth not, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth in heaven for vs:</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Which are kept by the power of God thorow faith vnto ſalvation, which is prepared to be ſhewed in the last time.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E muſt remember the trueth of that which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note> touching the thinges which God hath prepared for thoſe that love him, that they are ſuch, as neither eye hath ſeene, neither eare hath heard, nor hath come into the heart of man. Therefore did none of the Princes of this worlde knowe them, as ſaieth the ſame Apoſtle in the ſame place. For no naturall man perceyveth the things of the Spirit of God, neither can he know them becauſe they are ſpirituallie diſcerned, for
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177173:37"/>the wiſedome of God is a hidd wiſedome, cloſed in a myſterie, which is not given to every ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vnderſtand: yea the very chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God to whom God hath given his ſpirit, which ſearcheth all things, even the deepe things of God: although God doe reveile to them his ſecret, yet doe they ſee here but through a glaſſe,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12</note> darklie, as ſaith the Apoſtle. For our life (as witneſſeth the ſame Apoſtle to the Coloſſians) is hidd with Chriſt in God.
<note place="margin">Col. 3.3.</note> And as ſaith Ioh. in his firſt Epiſtle:
<note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.2.</note> Now are we the ſonns of God, but yet it is not made manifeſt what wee ſhalbe. For this cauſe we muſt content our ſelves in this life with the ſight which faith giveth vs, which is of that na ture &amp; force, as teſtifieth the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes, that it maketh things inviſible,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> to be evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and as it were viſible. For clearing of which ſight, and ſo conſequently, the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eſtabliſhing of our faith and further increaſe of our ſpirituall ioy, the Lord our God in his bleſſed worde doth ſet foorth thoſe inviſible things, vnder earthlie ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes of things knowen to vs: Thereby to leade our ſoules to the more livelie conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and clearer knowledge, what the hope of his calling is, and what the ritches of his glorious inheritance is in the Saints, that thereby we may be encouraged, with greater patience and conſtancie, to runne the race that is laid before vs, and to holde faſt the confeſſion of our hope without wavering vnto the ende: waiting ſtill for
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:177173:37"/>the manifeſtation of our bleſſed hope, in the glorious appearing of Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour. Therefore is it that the Apoſtle in this place, having ſpoken of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant mercie of God in begetting vs againe to the hope of lyfe: in the next place <hi>expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth</hi> the excellencie of this life hoped for, that thereby we may vnderſtande, that all things in this world are but vanitie, and in compariſon thereof nothing but dirt and dung, and ſo to be accounted loſſe that we may gaine it. Afterwards he declareth to vs the ſuertie &amp; certaintie which the Saintes have of enioying this lyfe hoped for: both in regard of the life, &amp; alſo of themſelves. So that here we have the other two points of conſolation, touching our hope, to bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered, wherof we did ſpeake in our laſt Sermon, to wit, the excellencie of the lyfe which wee looke for: and the certaintie of our attaining to it. The firſt is expreſſed in theſe wordes, <hi>to an inheritance immortall and vndefiled, and that withered not.</hi> The other, in the reſt of the words which we have read.</p>
            <p>In the firſt point we have two things to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider: one is the title or name which the Apoſtle giveth to our hope or life: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, the properties which he attributeth to it, by which he ſetteth before vs the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſnes &amp; excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of it: The title which he giveth it, is, That it is <hi>an inheritance.</hi> The properties are three, <hi>eternitie, puritie,</hi> and <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeablenes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſpeake then of the firſt: The Apoſtle
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:177173:38"/>calleth <hi>eternall life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eternall life is an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ſonnes, not to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaunts.</note> an inheritance, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme vs by what title we attaine vnto it, and by what right wee enioy it, to wit, by the right of heires. For ſeeing God only doth inherite immortalitie and life, as his proper poſſeſſion, we can never attaine to it till firſt we be made the heires of God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven coheires annexed with Chriſt Ieſus, who only is the righteous heire of all things, as ſaith the Apoſtle Paul to the Hebrues, becauſe hee is the onely Sonne of God. Now wee are made the heires of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.14.</note> by being firſt made his children, as ſaith the Apoſtle to the Romanes. If (ſaith he) we be children, we are alſo heires, even the heires of God, &amp; heires annexed with Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.5.</note> And againe to the Galathians: If thou be a ſonne, thou art alſo the heire of God through Chriſt. For it is manifeſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven among men, that the ſonne either by nature or by adoption, is counted for the heire. Now by nature we are not the ſonns of God,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.3.</note> but as ſaith the Apoſtle to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians, by nature we are the children of wrath, and by the redemption made by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, wee receive the adoption of the ſonnes, as witneſſeth the ſame Apoſtle to the Galathians.
<note place="margin">Gol. 4.5.</note> God ſending the ſpirit of his Sonne in our heartes, which cryeth <hi>Abba Father.</hi> Thus by Ieſus the only ſonne of God, &amp; ſo conſequentlie, his only heire by nature, we are firſt made the ſonnes of God, and ſo alſo the heires of this in heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of God. The vſe of this point is, to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:177173:38"/>inſtruct vs that we muſt not think to enioy eternall life as the reward of our ſervice, but as the right of heires, being made the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God: Chriſt in the eight of Iohn ſaith, that the ſervaunt abideth not in the houſe for ever, but the ſonne abideth for ever. Thereby informing vs, that hee who thinketh to dwell with God in his houſe eternallie, muſt needes be his ſon, ſo doeth the Apoſtle here teach vs, when he ſayth, that God begetteth vs againe to the hope of lyfe: declaring that wee muſt be borne of God, and ſo made the Sonnes of God, before wee can hope to inherite eternall lyfe. For whoſoever doth remaine in the houſe of God, noe other wayes, but as a ſervaunt, he ſhall at length be caſt out, and ſhalbe deprived of eternall lyfe, which is the inheritance of the ſonnes. Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſheweth, that al our ſervice is vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, even when wee have done all that wee can doe, if wee reſpect the merit of it. And the Saints themſelves confeſſe, that even their righteouſnes is polluted,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 69.6.</note> &amp; like a menſtruous cloth. How wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do they deceive their own ſoules, who build the hope of their life vpon merit of their workes. The Lord in <hi>Hagar</hi> the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, &amp; <hi>Iſmaell</hi> his ſonne, doth livelie repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the lot and portion of all the children of the lawe, that is, of all who by ſervice think to inherite heauen: having no other hope of eternall life then that which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred by the covenant of workes. <hi>Cast
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:177173:39"/>out,</hi> ſayeth the ſcripture, <hi>the ſervaunt with her ſonne:</hi> for the ſonne of the ſeruant ſhall not be heire with the ſonne of the free woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.30.</note> By this doth the Apoſtle to the Galathians ſhew, that which Chriſt ſaith to be true, to wit, that the ſervaunt ſhall not abide in the houſe for ever. Becauſe as the Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to caſt out <hi>Hagar</hi> the ſervaunt with her ſonne out of the houſe of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham which was the houſe of God, ſo shall he caſt out of his houſe, and deprive of the inheritaunce of eternal life, all thoſe who are not his ſonnes, but craue eternall life, as debt for reward of their workes.</p>
            <p>Now we come to the properties of this inheritance,
<note place="margin">The bleſſed eſtate of the Saints glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified.</note> which are three. It is called <hi>immortal, vndefiled, &amp; which withereth not.</hi> Theſe are the ſpeciall things which make a life happie and bleſſed: and the three contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries do make it miſerable and curſed. The three which make it happie are <hi>eternitie, purirte, and vnchangeablenes.</hi> The three con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries which make it miſerable, are <hi>morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie or death, ſinne or vneleannes, and chaungea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes or instabilstie.</hi> The ſpirit of God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by attributing thoſe three properties to our inheritance &amp; life which we hope for, doeth ſhew vs the excellencie &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes of our life wherevnto the Lord doth begett vs againe: thereby to teach vs that we loſe nothing, albeit wee looſe all things, if ſo be we gaine this life and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance. Let vs therefore conſider thoſe properties ſeverallie. The firſt is <hi>immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:177173:39"/>vnto an inheritance immortall, that is,
<note place="margin">The bleſſed eſtate of the Saintes in heaven im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall.</note> an inheritance or life which is no wayes ſubiect to corruption, but which indureth for ever: and therefore in the ſcriptures it is called <hi>eternall life,</hi> to diſtinguiſh it not only fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the life of beaſtes and other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but even from the life of man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which he hath by nature in this world We shall the more clearlie perceive the comfort of this poynt, if we conſider two things which the ſcriptures lay before our eyes. The firſt is, concerning that which is in greateſt price with man, for which hee laboureth chieflie, as the principall end of all his travels. The ſecond is the vanitie of his labor as touching that end, &amp; vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablenes of al his paines, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently the vnſpeakeable grief and ſorrow where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with his ſoule is pearched, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he findeth himſelf fruſtrat of his end. As for the firſt, The thing in the worlde moſt deare to a man, is his life, which gladly he would pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerve with the loſſe of al that ever he hath. Sathan did know this, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to provoke the Lord againſt Iob he vſeth this argument: <hi>skinne for skinne, and all that ever a man hath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>will he giue for his life.</hi> And Chriſt our Saviour, knowing that the love of this life doeth moſt of all ſway our actions, perceyving this foolish ſolicitude in Peter even to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, he sheweth his Apoſt. that <hi>who ſoever will ſaue his life ſhall loſe it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.25</note> How glad the worldly man would be, if he could live in this world eternally: this in deed is the foo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhnes
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:177173:40"/>of men, they thinke their houſes and habitations ſhall continue for ever: &amp; ſo rooted is the vanitie in mans heart, that albeit the Fathers that have thought ſo, doe die like the beaſtes: yet their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is not made the wiſer, but goe on in the fooliſh way of their fathers, and delight in their talke, as ſaith the ſpirit of God in the 49.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.6.7</note> Pſalme. mortall ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtryving vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to eterniſe him ſelfe in this perishing world. Which vanitie the Lord expreſſeth when he sheweth firſt that albeit a man by his labours obtaineth aboudance of all things,
<note place="margin">Luc 12.15</note> yet his life ſtandeth not in his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Which he cleareth by that parable of the rich man, who ſaid to his ſoule: ſoule thou haſt much goods laied vp for manie yeares, live at eaſe, eate, drinke, and take thy paſtime: but God ſaide vnto him, O foole, this night will they fetch away thy ſoule from thee: then whoſe shall thoſe things be which thou haſt provided? The ſecond argument of mans vanitie is, that as his life ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not in his aboundance, ſo can not all his aboundance preſerve a man from death, nor yet procure the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of one dead to life againe, as the Lord declareth in the 49. Pſalme.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 49.6.7.</note> neither can any redeeme his brother, nor give his raunſome to God (ſo precious is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of their ſoules, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for ever) that he may live ſtill for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 6.7.</note> and not ſee the grave. Thirdlie, Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſheweth that all the labour of man is
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:177173:40"/>for the mouth, yet the ſoule is not filled, and therefore man paineth him ſelfe in vaine, in traveling for the winde, ſeeing he never can fill his ſoule, nor ſatisfie his heart with all his labours. Laſtlie, ſayeth the Lord in the foreſaid Pſalme,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.17</note> Man ſhall take nothing away when he dieth, neither shall his pompe deſcend after him. When vaine man ſeeth this that all his labour is in vaine, ſeeing he can not thereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his life but he muſt die,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 2. &amp;c.</note> and lye like a sheepe in the grave, then doeth his ſoule abhorre all comfort, nothing is there in the world that can be able to make him reioyce,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 3.18.19. &amp;c.</note> feeing he muſt loſe that for which all other things are deſired, and without the which, al things do ſerve for nothing.
<note place="margin">Eccl. 2.15.16.</note> Salomon doth teach this, who ſeeing that he muſt die, and leave all his labours to the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that should be after him,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 2.17.18.</note> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in them ſelves were as beaſts, the condition of both being one: ſeeing as the one dieth ſo dieth the other: all go to one place: and all was of the duſt, and al shall returne to duſt: and perceyving that wiſedome, nor riches, nor ſtrength, &amp;c. made no difference but that it did befall to the wiſe as it did to the foole: then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan he to hate all his labour, yea even the life it ſelfe, becauſe it was to end. A moſt evident proove, that albeit a man doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye all pleaſures, riches, and honors, yea all whatſoever he traveleth for vnder the ſunne, or whatſoever his hart can wishe in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:177173:41"/>this world: yet is there no peace to the hart of him, nor ioye to the ſoule of him, nor happines in the eſtate of him, ſo long as he ſeeth he muſt die and his life muſt end, then doeth he with Salomon conclude, al, not onely to be vanitie, but alſo vexation of ſpirit: yea the more he doth poſſeſſe of theſe earthlie bleſſings, the greater is his miſerie, and more greevous are his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes when death cometh to plucke him from his houſe to the grave. Thus even the verie life of man, wherein is the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt comfort of man: by mortalitie, beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a grief to man, and a vexation to the ſpirit of man: For all the ioyes of this world, and all the comfortes of this life are eclipſed by death. This being rightlie weyghed and well conſidered, wee shall then apprehend what infinite conſolation this firſte propertie of the life, vnto the hope whereof our God hath begotten vs againe, doth miniſter vnto vs. for therein we ſee that taken away which alone is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make our life miſerable &amp; cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, even mortalitie and death, which is the curſe of God vpon ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſinne. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie let a man looke to his life, albeit in the eyes of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> never ſo happie, yet if he looke to it as it is in deed, that is to ſaye mortall and deadlie, although it be buſked with all the beauties of this world, and fortified with all the ſtrength of this worlde, and crowned with all the glorie of this world, yet shall he never haue comfort in it: and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:177173:41"/>it is moſt certaine that they ſee not what this life is who glorie in it: and it is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie blindnes of their eyes which do not let them ſee their end, that maketh the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of this world to reioyce in any thing vnder the ſunne, ſeeing all ſhal periſh and come to nought. No, No, they ſee not life to reioyce in, that ſeeth not this life of the children of God, vnto the hope where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Lord begetteth them: This is the ground of the reioycing and gloriation of the Saintes, ſaith the Apoſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, even the hope of this inheritance which is immortall. And this ſame ſight of this immortalitie of that lyfe was the thing that mooved the Apoſtle himſelfe to deſire with ſighes to change this earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie tabernacle with that which is not made with handes, but is of God. For hee did knowe that it was eternall, therefore deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hee to be clothed with it, even to this end, that mortalitie might be ſwallowed vp of lyfe. This then is the comfort of this firſt propertie, that death ſhall have noe dominion over our lyfe in heaven, but it ſhall remaine for evermore: And herein ſtandeth one of the chief pointes of the happines and felicitie of the Saints in the world to come, that their inheritance is immortal. All whatſoever a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inheriteth in this worlde, is mortall, his life here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, but in the world to come, it endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth eternallie. <hi>The honour, ritches and pleaſures of this world, periſh: but in heaven there is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:177173:42"/>for vs an induring ſubſtance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.34</note> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Hebrewes. <hi>And the pleaſures which are at the right hand of God, are for evermore,</hi> ſaith David:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe heavens ſhall paſſe away, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements ſhall melt with heate, and this earth with the workes that are therein ſhalbe burnt vp,</hi> ſayeth Peter:
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.10 &amp; 13.</note> but we hope for new heavens and a newe earth, according to the promiſe of God, wherein dwelleth rigeteouſnes. So whatſoever we vnderſtand by this inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, all is eternall in the world to come, the life eternal, the heavens, the earth, the glory, the riches, the pleaſures, the reaſt, theioy that we ſhal enioy eternal. The firſt vſe of this point is, to make vs who doe finde nothing perfectly, happie, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, which is ſubiect to mortalitie, to take our hearts and affections of this peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing life and world, and to caſt away the love of corruptible things, and to beholde and affect the lyfe &amp; bleſſings that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent and everlaſting. The ſecond vſe is to comfort vs againſt two tentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we have to fight: the one is touching our preſent eſtate and feeling: the other is touching the feare that might enter in our mindes of that might befall vs in the poſſeſſion of this life of God in heaven. In this preſent lyfe wee have not onely to looke for an ende of our lyfe and of all creatures, but the Saintes they have a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the dayly decay of the outwarde man, &amp; themſelves haſting to an end: now this death that cometh in betwixt vs and our hope for lyfe, can not but ſometimes
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:177173:42"/>trouble and grievouſlie torment the mind that hath no ſight of that immortall ſtate to come: Therefore the wicked are weary in beating of affliction, and are altogether vnable to digeſt the dolours and paynes which they conceive of death: having no ſence, nor ſight, nor hope of a permanent and endles life: but the godly man, who findeth his inward man renewing daylie, and feeling in himſelfe the powers of the world to come, and being eſtabliſhed by hope, he is ſo farre from fainting with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent afflictions, that he reioyceth in them, as ſaith the Apoſtle to the Romanes,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.3.</note> and ſo farre is hee from being diſcouraged or affraid of death, that he chuſeth rather to be diſſolved: yea many haue refuſed to be delivered from death, that they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a better reſurrection. O if this wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched world did knowe what great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage the man renewed hath aboue him who is not renewed, in the time of trouble and affliction, and ſpeciallie in the houre of death, which putteth an end to all the ioyes of this life: howe much would they eſteeme, of that renewing grace that brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth men to the hope of an inheritance immortall: and how carefull would they be to finde themſelves begotten againe to the hope of this inheritance before that heavie day of death doe come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, that they might have comfort againſt the terrour of it, by the ſence and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the life of God begunne in their
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:177173:43"/>ſoules, which never can be ended, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perfited by the death of our fleſh, the ſoule that hopeth even in dying, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending eternall life: ſo the hope of this inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which is immortall, doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs againſt the mortalitie of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſtate, and future ruine and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this preſent world. The ſecond vſe is, to comfort vs againſt that which we might feare ſhould happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs being poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt againe with the life of God in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loſſe of that life againe: the grounds of this feare may be the experience paſt in Adam and in Angells: Adam being crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the likenes of God, &amp; being placed in Paradiſe, did nevertheles loſe his perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and lyfe, and was thruſt out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. Thus left to himſelfe, hee could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther keepe his lyfe nor the poſſeſſion of Paradiſe, but looſed both by obeying Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, who did ſlay him in making him to ſinne.
<note place="margin">Iud. 6.</note> The Angels that were in heaven with God, did not keepe their firſt eſtate wherein they were created, &amp; which they did enioy in the preſence of God, and now are reſerved vnder darknes vnto the iudgement of the great day. Who would not feare at theſe examples to be deprived of lyfe, although once poſſeſſed with it, &amp; that alſo in heaven? Death having over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen the life both of man &amp; Angell, even then when they enioyed all perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life, the one in Paradiſe, the other in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:177173:43"/>heaven. What then is our conſolation, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, that our lyfe which in Chriſt we reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, is more ſure then the life which Adam had, even then the life whiche Angells had by creation, for theirs was ſubiect to haſarde, but our life is exempt from all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſard of death: therefore are we not to feare that it ſhall befall ſo to vs any more, as it did to them: For our inheritance which we looke for is permanent and immortall, therefore after our reſurrection wee shall bee no more in feare nor daunger of death, <hi>For this corruptible ſhall put on incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and this mortall ſhal put on immortality,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.53.</note> 
               <hi>and then ſhall death be ſwallowed vp into victory, &amp; mortality ſhalbe ſwallowed vp of lyfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.4.</note> and death it ſelfe, that laſt enemie in that day ſhalbe deſtroyed: for death and hell ſhalbe caſt into the lake of fire,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.26. Revel. 20.14. 1 Cor. 15.55.</note> which is the ſeconde death, then ſhal we ſing moſt ioyfully that ſong of triumph: <hi>O death where is they ſting: O grave wher is thy victory:</hi> Thus this firſt point doth enceedingly comfort vs, &amp; giveth vs ample matter of glorifying God, that hee called vs, who are mortall and corruptible creatures, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this miſerable eſtate, to a life that endureth for ever: yet doth this next property of this life and inheritance much more comfort the true children of God, who have no further pleaſure in life it ſelf, then ſo farre as it doeth ſerve to the glory of God, albeit the wicked take no care of diſhonoring God, ſo being they may live.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:177173:44"/>For hee that is truely wyſe, knoweth that the life which ſerveth no wayes to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, ſhall never procure honour to him that enioyeth it. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of his lyfe is nothing benefited by his lyfe, it were better for him never to have had lyfe, ſeeing it muſt needes in the end procure his greater harme, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing God is holines it ſelfe, and ſo by conſequence, a mortall enemie of all vncleannes, there can be no happines in a lyfe that is vncleane and polluted. For it ſtandeth ſure which the Apoſtle ſayeth,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> 
               <hi>That without holines, no man ſhall ſee God.</hi> For this cauſe it is, that the Saints ſighe continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in this life,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.4.</note> becauſe of the burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſin wherewith they are burdened, knowing that a neceſſitie of ſinning is laid vpon vs, whyle we walk in this earthly tabernacle, and therefore with the Apoſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> finding that we are ſolde vnder ſin, ſo that in our fleſh ther dwelleth no good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and albeit by the grace of God to will be preſent with vs, yet we finde no meanes to performe that which is good, becauſe although we delite in the Law of God, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the inward man, yet we ſtil ſee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other law in our me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, rebelling againſt the law of the minde, and leading vs cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive vnto the law of ſinne, which is in our members. Therfore I ſay with the Apoſtle: wee are compelled to crie out againſt our lyfe, <hi>O wretched men that we are, who ſhall deliver vs from this body of death,</hi> ever wiſhing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:177173:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be freed from this lyfe that is pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, and in the which wee can not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our ſelves from vncleanes. And this is the ſecond cauſe why this preſent life is miſerable in all men, of what ſoever eſtate they be: all men without exception being defiled with ſinne, even from their firſt conception,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note> 
               <hi>as being both conceyved and berne in ſinne:</hi> and therefore is it that the Saintes deſire to be diſſolved, becauſe they know (as ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that if their earthlie houſe of this tabernacle were deſtroyed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>they haue a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding given of God,</hi> that is an <hi>houſe not made with ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, but eternal in the heavens:</hi> In which houſe they ſhall ſinne no more, <hi>becauſe corruption ſhalbe ſwallowed vp of incorruption.</hi> By this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence now, betwixt this preſent ſinful life, &amp; that bleſſed life in holines, to the which wee are begotten againe, doeth appeare the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of the one aboue the other, &amp; ſo doth give iuſt occaſion to al the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to caſt the love of this life, &amp; all things in it farre from them: being ſo diſpoſed by the grace of God, that they can not love, nor like that, whereby their God is diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored, &amp; with as earneſt dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to preaſſe forward to that other lyfe, which they ſee to be freed from all vncleannes, &amp; ſo from all occaſion of offending or diſhonoring their God. And yet further to weigh the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of this point, we muſt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in the former, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth vs that this inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. Theſe two, ſo ſtill accompanie one
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:177173:45"/>another, that the one that is immortality, can not be without this other property of vndefilednes. For death is the rewarde of ſinne,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> ſo that were ſinne is not, there is no death. Hereby appeareth that excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of this lyfe, in that it is exempt from ſinne, and ſo conſequently from death: ſo that this propertie may very well be called, the cauſe of the other whiche precedeth, that is, Immortalitie: Like as Immortalitie may be compted the cauſe of the laſt property, that is vnchangeablenes, <hi>for ſinne is the ſting of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.56.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle. And therefore take away ſinne, which is the thing that defileth both vs and our lyfe, yea the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, the earth, and al creatures, death ſhal have nothing wherewith to annoy vs: the ſtrength of death, which is ſinne, being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away. Now to come to the vſe of this point, it ſerveth for a threefolde comfort to man, when either hee looketh to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder grace in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t world, or to the eſtate of man in his firſt creation, or yet to the eſtate of Angels in their firſt creation. In his eſtate vnder grace, albeit he have begun to live the life of God, yet ſtill as wee have ſaid, he findeth a rebellion of ſinn in his fleſh, reſiſting the will of God in his minde, which wee have sheweth to be a matter of continuall grief to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, now to the heart oppreſſed with this godlie ſorrow for ſinne, that daylie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth him, what can bee more comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then that hope of that lyfe, in the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:177173:45"/>which he shall ceaſe from ſinne, and bee wholy freed from all the bondes &amp; cordes of iniquitie in the ful freedome and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of holines. Herewith did the Apoſtle take vp him ſelfe from his griefe, in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation wherein he lamented his owne miſerie, in the ſeventh Chap. to the Rom. After hee had ſaide:
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>O miſerable man that I am, who ſhal deliver me from the body of this death?</hi> Looking to that bleſſed eſtate of perfect holines, vnto the which we were called by God in Chriſt, he addeth theſe wordes of conſolation, to recreate his owne ſoule: I thanke my God through Ieſus Chriſt my Lorde. This maketh the heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, which never could otherwayes have perfite pleaſure nor ioy in the beginnings of grace, righteouſnes and holines graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this lyfe, no not in the greateſt meaſure, that ever was given by Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus to any creature: but this hope of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie maketh vs not to faint nor wearie in our mindes, ſtriving againſt ſinne, but patiently to fight vnto the end, wayting for that bleſſed hope. Now if man looke further vnto that caſe wherein Adam was in Paradiſe albeit in the eſtate of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without ſinne, yet ſinne did prevayle over him, and did both defile him, and all other things to him. Furthermore, the Angels that were created in perfection, yet did not ſtand in their firſt eſtate, but were overcome by ſinn. So ſtrong a thing is ſin, that neither man in his integritie, nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells in their glorie, were able to reſiſt it.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:177173:46"/>Here now appeareth vpon the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this propertie of our inheritance, how exceeding more happie is our eſtate in Chriſt, then was the eſtate of Adam by creation: yea the eſtate of Angells in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Their eſtate was ſubiect to falling, as doleful experience in both did prove, but in this eſtate wherevnto wee are renewed in Chriſt, there is no poſſibilitie of ſinning any more, after we are poſſeſt with our life in the heavens and ſo the feare of the like miſerie which might ariſe in our heartes vpon their fall, is quite taken away: for our life and inheritance is vndefiled. For when we ſhal enioy the fruite of our high Prieſtes oblation and reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliation,
<note place="margin">Heb. 7.26.</note> as he is holy, harmeles, vndefiled, ſeperate from ſinners, and made higher the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heavens, ſo ſhall wee alſo be holy, harmeles, vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, ſeperate from ſinners, and made hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gher then the heavens. So then when our God ſhalbe al in vs all, ſinne ſhall haue no more place in our minde, in will, in affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor any parte of our fleſh. And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as now to thoſe that are defiled, nothing is pure,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> but even their mindes and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are defiled. So then when wee shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be vndefiled, all things shall be cleane to vs, the heavens, the earth and all things, becauſe wee our ſelves, our mindes and conſciences shalbe cleane: and therefore is it that wee waite for new heavens, and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. For in that kingdome, wherin no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:177173:46"/>thing shall enter, all things shalbe cleane, &amp; ſo eſtablished in cleannes, that nothing shalbe able to defile them for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Here is the comfort for them that mourne in this life for their owne ſinnes, and the ſinnes and abominations that are committed in the middes of the houſe of God, even that they them ſelves, and the whole houſe of God,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 9.24.</note> shalbe delivered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> filthines of ſinn, being poſſeſt with that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting righteouſnes which is brought in by the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God.
<note place="margin">The Saints in heaven not ſubiect to change.</note> Now followeth the third propertie of our inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which is <hi>that it withereth not.</hi> This maketh vp the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our eſtate in heaven: for nothing can make a man happie, which is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and ſtable without change. The rich man is not made happie by his vncertaine riches, becauſe as Iob, he may be turned to povertie, and his habitation made deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. So is it of all things earthlie: for there is nothing conſtant vnder the ſunne, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all is but vanitie. It is true that not only the wicked but even ſometimes the children of God, being in proſperite, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be brought to ſay:
<note place="margin">Iob. 29.18.19. Pſal. 10.6. Pſal. 30.6.</note> 
               <hi>That they ſhall dye in their Neſt: that their roote is ſpread out by the water, and therefore they ſhall never be mooved, nor ſuffer any changes,</hi> but they finde when the Lord shall hide his face, that they are troubled and their eſtate changed. Moreover, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit all other things should continew af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one, yet mans owne frayeltie maketh his life miſerable: for albeit he grew vp in
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:177173:47"/>ſtrength and activenes, yet age cometh &amp; changeth him: So that the moyſture of his life being dried vp, they wither as graſſe, even as the herbe and graſſe of the field, &amp; trees of the forreſt, albeit they floriſh in ſummer, yet in winter they wither, and looſe all their beautie of their life.
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.24.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doeth de ſpirit of God compare all fleſh to graſſe,
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.10.</note> and the glorie of fleſh to the floure of the graſſe, becauſe as the graſſe withereth and the floure falleth away:
<note place="margin">Eſai. 40.6.</note> ſo doeth alſo all fleſh, and all the glorie of fleſh wither and fall away, and ſo by time is worne out. The conſideration of this poynt made <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of God, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the miſerie of mans life, laying it out before the Lord, ſaying: Man in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, he groweth like the graſſe: inde the morning it floriſheth and groweth, but in the evening it is cut downe and withereth: <hi>the time of our life is threeſcore yeares and tenne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.5.</note> 
               <hi>and if they be of ſtrength, foure ſcore yeares:</hi> yet the ſtrength is but labour and ſorrow, for it is cut of quicklie, and we flie away. Now although a life were everlaſting and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from ſinne, yet could it not bring perfect contentement to man, except it were ſuch as could ſuffer no alteration. If the ſtrong man could continew eternallie in his ſtrength, and not become weake, he might have ioy in his eſtate: and ſo alſo the beautifull man: the rich man: the honorable man, &amp;c. but let a man be in never ſo good eſtate, in this life, and as
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:177173:47"/>contented with his eſtae, as flesh can be, yet all his contentement is taken from him by the neceſſitie of Change, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all things vnder the ſunne are ſubiect. Therefore for fulfilling of our ioye, our God hath prepared a life and inheritance for vs in Chriſt, which withereth not: but looke what glorie, ſtrength, power and maieſtie wee shalbe indewed with at the comming of Chriſt in that ſame glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſtrentgh, power, and beautie of life, and in that ſame meaſure wee shall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new for ever without changes: our life and inheritance ſuffering neither dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution nor alteration of ſtrength, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>autie, nor glorie, but ſtill florishing in the perfection of ſtrength, beautie, glorie, and riches, and honour. This sheweth and teacheth vs what is the difference betwixt this preſent life and the life to come. This life is not perfited at the firſt, but receyved increaſe and grouth, till we come to the perfite ſtature and ſtrength of a man. Therefore it continueth not ſo, but admitteth decreaſe &amp; daylie diminution, till at length after long withering, it bee all conſumed, but in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the firſt we are exalted to the acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plished perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licite: &amp; in that perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we shal continew etenallie: our glorie never beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming leſſe: our ioye never diminishing: our beautie never fading: our ſtrength never impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. What would not a man ſuffer for ſuch a life, and what would he not forſake,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:177173:48"/>to the end he might enioy this life. The world muſt either bee blinde, or beaſtlie without meaſure, that doth not long to be out of this world, that they may enioye this bleſſed eſtate, that never changeth. This ſerveth to comfort vs in the changes of this preſent lyfe, becauſe we know that our eſtate in heaven ſhalbe exempt from all changes, and to incourage vs againſt al feare that can come vpon the change that came vpon Adam his life in Paradiſe: who being without ſhame, yet was turned to a ſhamefull ſtate. But to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude this point, the Apoſtle to the Corinthes ſetteth forth moſt livelie theſe three properties of our eſtate in heaven, in the deſcription of our Reſurrection from the dead, opponing the preſent condition of our bodies to the future qualities in heaven, and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth the difference in theſe three ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.42.</note> 
               <hi>That our bodies are ſowen in corruption, &amp; are raiſed in incorruption: they are ſowen in diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp; are raiſed in glorie: they are ſowen in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; rayſed in power.</hi> And he concludeth by the fourth point, which is as it were the cauſe of the other three, to wit, <hi>that they are ſowen naturall bodies, &amp; are raiſed ſpirituall bodyes.</hi> Hereby incorruption is expreſſed, the firſt propertie of our <hi>inheritance</hi> here mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which is <hi>immortalitie:</hi> &amp; in the ſecond is comprehended <hi>vndefilednes:</hi> and in the third this <hi>vnchangeablenes.</hi> For our lyfe shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be immortall, becauſe we shalbe raiſed in incorruption: and our vile bodies, disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177173:48"/>for ſinne and frutes thereof, shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be raiſed in glorie, and therefore free from being defiled any more: &amp; the cauſe why our life shall not wither, is, becauſe that our bodyes that are here weake, shalbe rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in power, &amp; the cauſe of all theſe three conſiſteth, in the different manner of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that we have here, and shall have in the heavens, becauſe our bodies here are naturall bodies, or animate bodies after the life of Adam, who was created a living ſoule: therfore is our lyfe ſubiect to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie, dishonour and changes, for a ſoule can not give immortalitie, puritie, nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeablenes to a body, but in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens our bodyes shalbe ſpirituall bodyes, after the life of Chriſt, who was made a quickening ſpirit: for by the ſpirit of life that is in Chriſt Ieſus, shall wee live alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither in heaven, God being all in all. The principall vſe of this poynt, beſides theſe before ſpoken, is to comfort vs in tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this preſent life, when we finde our ſpirituall changes, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our life in Chriſt: for the ſpirituall man is not at all tymes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, his faith being ſometimes ſo ſtrong, that he dareth boaſt with David, that <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he walked throw the Galley of the ſhadow of death, yet would he feare none evill:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.4.</note> 
               <hi>and though an hoaſt pitcheth against him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.3.</note> 
               <hi>yet his hart ſhould not be afraid.</hi> At other times his faith becommeth ſo weake, being ſore aſſaulted, <hi>that his heart fayleth him:</hi> yea even at ſmall occaſions. Peter that even now did boaſt, though all
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:177173:49"/>the world should forſake his Lord, yet would he never forſake him. At the voyce of a maide, is brought to forſweare him. The ſpirituall man ſuſtayning the ſame changes that doth the naturall man The naturall life which now doth florish in ſtrength and beautie, doth ſuffer changes by ſicknes, by age, and by affliction, that ſometimes it weakneth, ſometimes it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be quite away, when it is oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſo that the body lyeth as dead in a tranuce, even ſo the ſpirituall lyfe hath the ſame fits, ſometimes the Chriſtian ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving great difficultie to hold his hope, and ſometimes being forced to mourne, as one alreadie among the dead, and one ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth cleane away from the preſence of God, all ſence of the life of God being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by ſome extraordinarie tentation, or to great ſecuritie in ſpirituall exerciſes. This doth even the ſpirituall man finde, that in his ſpirituall life, although it never be taken away, yet doth it many wayes ſeeme to decay, and ſometymes vtterlie to be gone: againſt this griefe have we to comfort our ſelves with the hope of this eſtate in the which our life shall never any more be ſubiect to changes,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 77. Pſal. 98.</note> neither shall our ſoules be vexed with ſuch tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as now doe bring the ſtrongeſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian oftentimes to a moſt pitifull weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſo that their ſoule refuſeth comfort, and become ſo aſtonished, that they can not ſpeake, and ſo filled with evill, that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:177173:49"/>they ſeeme to be cut off, doubting of their life. And that which I ſpeake of faith, I ſpeake alſo of the remayning partes of our life: of our love to God and his Sanits: our ſanctification: our zeale: our ioy: our peace: which all ſometimes floriſh, ſometimes fade and wither. Which all in the life to come ſhall remaine eternallie, and ſtill flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in their ful perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thus much tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the excellencie of our inheritance. Now followeth the third poynt,
<note place="margin">The cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of ſalvation.</note> which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſuretie of this inheritance, which is the third thing that worketh the fulnes of our ioy, when we know that ther is a life after this life to be hoped for, and that this life is moſt excellent. And laſtlie, that it is impoſsible to fruſtrate vs of this life. The other two doe provoke a thirſt and earneſt deſire of this life, but the third bringeth peace and conſolation to the man that longeth for it: when hee knoweth aſſuredlie that hee shall have it. Whereas the contrarie is a verie hell to the conſcience. For when it is given to a man to know there is a life prepared for a man in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that this life is ſo excellent, that there is nothing worthie of it in this world: What grief and vnſpeakeable ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe muſt it breed to him, to be deprived of that eſtate, wherein he ſeeth ſuch feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie? <hi>Eſau,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 27.</note> when he heard that he was deprived of the bleſſing, following the birthright, he cryed out with a great crie and bitter out of meaſure, ſayeth the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:177173:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpirit of God: for hee would haue inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the bleſſing, and therefore ſought it with teares, but hee was reiected, ſaith the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> &amp; found no place to repentance in his Father. This is the iuſt iudgement of God againſt all prophane perſons, who preferre in their worldlie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, the pleaſures of this life to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirtance of the life to come: to make their vaine and fruitles deſires of that life, to torment their mindes.
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1. Iud. 11.</note> The ſame moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Balaam,</hi> that prophane prophete, which loved the wages of vnrighteouſnes (ſeeing the bleſſed end of the righteous, but no wayes aſſured to enioy it) to crie out:
<note place="margin">Num. 23.</note> O let me dye the death of the righteous, and let my laſt end be like his. So deadlie a wound doth pearce the ſoule that findeth no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of that life, wherein conſiſteth all felicitie. Therefore to make vs pertakers of that ſolide conſolation which is proper to the godlie, our God doeth let vs ſee how ſure &amp; certaine this life is to al that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to the hope of it. For it is this cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine aſſurance of the enioying of it that worketh ſtrong conſolation in the Saints, as is manifeſt by the wordes of the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes,
<note place="margin">Heb. 5.17.18. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>willing more aboundantlie to ſhew vnto the hetres of promiſe the ſtablenes of his counſell, bound him ſelfe by an eath, that by two immutable things, wherein it is impoſſible that God ſhould lie, we might have ſtrong conſolation: who haue our refuge, to lay holde vpon that hope, that is ſet before vs.</hi> Declaring here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:177173:50"/>that the ſtrength of our ioye, dependeth vpon the infalliblenes of our hope. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it, that David doeth pray to God in the hundreth and ſixt Pſalme,
<note place="margin">Pſal 106.4. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>That he would remember him with the favour of his people, &amp; that hee would viſitie him with his ſalvation.</hi> To that end he ſubioyneh himſelfe that ſayth. <hi>That I may ſee the felicitie of thy choſen, &amp; ſo reioyce in the ioy of thy people, and glorie with thine inheritance.</hi> Shewing that without ſight of this felicitie and certaine aſſurance of it, no heart can ioy nor glorie, as doe the children of God. We come therefore to conſider this poynt, which is ſet downe to vs in two partes, according to the two folde daunger which may ſeeme to be in the attayning to this life. The firſt is, in the life it ſelfe, to know that it be ſure. The ſecond is in vs, to know that wee be ſure to that life. For if either that life might be taken away from vs, or yet that we could be taken away from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying that life, there could bee no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of it to our ſoules. Therefore firſt the Apoſtle declareth, how this life is kept for vs. Next, he ſheweth how we are kept for it: that neither it can be taken away from vs, nor wee from it. The keeping of it is ſet downe in theſe wordes: <hi>Reſerved in the heavens for vs:</hi> and the keeping of vs to it, in the wordes following: <hi>who are kept by the power of God through faith vnto ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And laſtlie, the time of the manifeſtation of it, is ſet downe to vs by the Apoſtle, ſaying: <hi>Which is prepared to be ſhewed in the last time.</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:177173:51"/>As touching the firſt parte of the ſuretie of our life, it conſiſteth firſt in the keeping of it.
<note place="margin">God the keeper of our life.</note> Secondlie, in the place where it is kept. And third lie in the end wherefore it is kept in the heavens. <hi>It is kept</hi> (ſayeth the Apoſtle) <hi>in the heaven, and that for vs.</hi> Firſt then we will ſpeake of the keeping of it, which bringeth great conſolation to the beleeving ſoule. Angells loſt their life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord did not keepe it to them: And Adam loſt his life likewiſe, becauſe it was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to his owne keeping. But now the Lord doth no more commit the keeping of our life in Chriſt to our ſelves, becauſe we ſhould doubtleſſe looſe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. For if man in his integritie was not able to keepe his life: how much leſſe is he able to doe it in his corruption and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie? yea the verie Angels, that yet doe continew in the life of God, were not able to indure, if God did not preſerve them in that life. Bleſſed therfor be God, who hath taken in his owne hande the cuſtodie of our life. The Apoſtle doeth herein co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort him ſelfe againſt the ſhame of the Croſſe, which he did ſuffer for preaching the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, ſaying: <hi>For which cauſe I alſo ſuffer theſe things:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Timoth. 1.20,</note> 
               <hi>But I am not aſhamed, for I know whom I haue beleeved,</hi> &amp;c. This made Paul reioyce, that God was able to keep his life, to whom he had committed it. And this is the great mercie of our God towards vs, that he doth take the care of keeping our life him ſelf. Sathan is moſt carefull, ſometimes againſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:177173:51"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelves, ſometimes againſt our life: for when he can not prevaile againſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to entiſe him to ſinne, and ſo to death, then doth he aſſaile his life, putting at his faith, to ſee if he can wreſt from him his confidence in God: knowing that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our perſons followeth the loſſe of our ſpirituall life in Chriſt. But thankes be to God, that it is not in our hande to looſe our life, ſince it is not committed to our keeping. And therefore in our greateſt tentations, when it ſeemeth, according to our ſenſe and feeling, that Sathan hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from vs, our peace, our ioy, our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, our confidence, our light, and communion with our God: ſo that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to vs, that we are vtterlie forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of God, &amp; all hope of life taken from vs: yet we may boldlie anſwere, that our life is not loſt, although all ſenſe be taken from vs of it: for our life is not in our kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, but in his, who is ſtronger then all, &amp; therefore no tentation is able ſo to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vs, that we bee compelled to caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our confidence in God, who is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>vnto whom in all our ſufferings according to his will, we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit our ſoules in wel doing, as to a faithfull Creator:</hi> according to the exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Apoſt. Pet. in his 1. Epi. cha. 4. &amp; 19. verſe. For he doth not expone our life to hazard, as he did the life of Angels &amp; of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe. The gates of hel are not able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt the elect of God in Chriſt, ſince God him ſelfe is the keeper of their life.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:177173:52"/>The ſecond part is,
<note place="margin">Our life is in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</note> concerning the place, where it is kept, and that is, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Heaven.</hi> Doubtles, it is much more ſure which is layd vp in heaven the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is kept in earth, for there Sathan hath no ſuch acceſſe, nor power to execute his craft and malice,
<note place="margin">Iob. 1.7.</note> as he hath in the earth. For his labour is, in compaſſing the earth to &amp; fro, as he ſayeth himſelfe in the booke of Iob. Therefore whatſoever is taken out of the earth, and put in the heavens, is exempt from all daunger of the Divilles malice. Therefore is it that our God willing to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs that our lyfe is in no daunger, doth ſhew vs that it is in the heavens. For that which wee enioy here in this worlde, is an earneſt of our lyfe, but not the life it ſelfe. For it is true which the Apo.
<note place="margin">Col. 3.3.</note> ſayth to the Coloſſians: <hi>That we are dead, and that our lyſe is hid with Chriſt in God.</hi> The vſe of this point is, to make vs lift vp our mind to thoſe things which are aboue, as the Apoſtle in that ſame place exhorteth vs, and to ſet our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections on theſe things which are aboue, becauſe our lyfe is above with Chriſt, and therefore it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vs to have our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3 20.</note> as Citizens of the heaven: From whence we look for the Saviour, even the Lord leſus, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently for our lyfe, for our lyfe is with him:
<note place="margin">Col. 3.4.</note> and when he ſhall appeare from heaven, then ſhall our life alſo appeare with him. Therefore ought we to mortifie our members, which are on the earth. For where ſhall a mans heart be but where his treaſure is, &amp; what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be our
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:177173:52"/>treaſure more then our lyfe? Therefore heavie is the iudgement that the Apoſtle teacheth againſt them that minde earthlie things, writing to the Philippians.
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.18 19.</note> There is nothing can moove a man more to ſeek for heaven, then this, to know, that his life is there, and nothing can ſerve to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate our love of this world, &amp; of all things in this world, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, to know they belong not to our life, which conſiſteth not in them, nor in any thing vnder the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, ſeing that it is in the heavens. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over this warneth the godlie, with the Apoſtle Paul, to thinke, that they have not yet attayned to the Reſurrection from the dead, or that they are already perfect;
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.12 &amp;c.</note> ſo long as they are in this world, ſeeing their life is not in this world: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that they ought to forget that which is behynde, &amp; indevour the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves to that which is before, and follow harde toward the mark, for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus. Further, it is a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler comfort againſt the fall of Adam: For hee had his life in Paradiſe, but not in the heavens, therefore was his lyfe ſubiect to ſpoyle, whereas ours is in the heavens, and therefore not ſubiect to ſpoile. And yet to augment our ioy in this point, wee have to conſider that which the Apoſtle ſayeth to the Coloſſians concerning our lyfe. <hi>It is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hid with Chriſt in God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.3.</note> Firſt it is hidd. Secondlie it is hid with Chriſt. Thridlie, it is hidd with Chriſt in God. Wee our ſelves, who have further ſight of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:177173:53"/>things that are above, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sathan hath, do not ſee our lyfe, it is yet hid fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, for <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver eye did ſee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>nor eare hath heard, neither came in mans heart, thethings which God hath prepared for them that love him:</hi> much more then is it hid from Sathan, that he can not ſee it. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is hid with Chriſt, even with him who hath given his life for it, and purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to vs by his owne death. It can bee with none to whom we can more ſecurely credit it, or who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> have more care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it.
<note place="margin">Iohan. 17.12.</note> He was faithfull in all that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did commit to him, for none of them that the Father gave him,
<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.2.</note> did he loſe: And this is the Fathers will, that he ſhould give eternall life to all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the Father hath given him, &amp; this life that he ſhould give vs, is with him who ſhould give it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be in ſure keeping: yea more it is hid with him, becauſe he is our life it ſelfe, and now hee being taken out of our ſight, and hid in the heavens, our life can not be ſeene, til he be ſeene againe: this is the ſuretie of our lyfe, that it is with our Savior. Who in purchaſing of it, did ſpoyle the principalities,
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.17 Ephe 1.22. Coloſ. 2.10</note> and powers, and made a ſhew of them openlie, and triumphed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them in the Croſſe: to whom all things are ſubdued, &amp; who is the head of all prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality and power. Thirdly, it is in God. O what a comfort is this, that the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is the place, even the Coffer or Chriſt, in the which our life is kept, ſo that Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt ſpoyle God himſelfe, before he be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſpoyle our life. The damned Angels
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:177173:53"/>had their life in the heavens, but kept in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves, &amp; therfore loſt they it. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the keeping of our life in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth vs againſt the feare of the lyke loſſe that befell to Adam, who had his life in earthlie Paradiſe, vnto the which Sathan found acceſſe: So this keeping of it with Chriſt in God, aſſureth vs againſt the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the Angells fall. This now concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the place where our life is kept. Now followeth the end wherfore it is kept,
<note place="margin">Life is kept for vs.</note> and that is for vs, ſaith the Apoſtle. It were no comfort to vs how ſurely ſoever this inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, were kept by God, if God did keepe it for Angells, or if he did keepe it for any other creature, or for himſelf on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For no happines of any other creature could co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort me, I being my ſelf depriued of it: but here is our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, that we know, this life which is kept by God in heaven, is kept for vs, &amp; for none other. Therfore the wicked, who have no aſſurance to gert this life, have no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort in the ſure keeping of it. The very ſpeech of the Apoſtle leadeth vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider That bleſſed is the man, who is in the fellowſhip of the clect, for whom this life is ordained, that he may ſay, as the Apoſtle doth here, That hee is one of the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that life is kept. This is the maner of the Saintes ſpeach, becauſe they ſee that it is in the communion of Saintes, that they enioy all the bleſſings of God in Chriſt. Therefore to ſpeake of their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying of them in this fellowſhip, as being of that number. This is the third thing
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:177173:54"/>that sheweth the ſuretie of this life to vs, even becauſe it is for vs that God keepeth it. It was doubtles a great tentation to the poore <hi>Cananitiſh</hi> woman of <hi>Sarophenica,</hi> when ſhe heard Chriſt ſay, that hee was not ſent but to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell: and yet more heavie, when ſhe heard him ſay to hir, That it was not good to take the childrens bread, and to caſt it to dogges, as though he had neither ben ſent to her, nor yet had gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſation of grace, to beſtow ought on her therof, &amp; if her faith had not overcome this aſſault, it had bene better for her never to have kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, that he was the Lord of life, ſent into the world for the life thereof: but her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation could not be taken from her, nor her confidence drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of her heart, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee did ſee through faith in him, that even the dogges of the Gentiles were to eate of the crummes of the childrens ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. This alſo made the Gentiles to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in their hearts &amp; be glad, when they heard of the Apoſtle Paul,
<note place="margin">Act. 13.48.</note> that God had ordained Chriſt a Saviour, &amp; a light to the Gentiles. when before they heard of the promiſe made to the Iewes, and fulfilling thereof in Chriſt, in whom forgivenes of ſinnes was preached, &amp; deſired &amp; beſought the Apoſtles Paul and Barnabas, that they would preach theſe wordes to them the next Sabbath day. Doubtles they would haue given all the world, to haue ben ſure that that conſolation which was preached
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:177173:54"/>to the Iewes, might alſo haue belonged to them. And therefore when the next Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day they had it, out of the Apoſtles mouth, confirmed by the ſcripture, that God had made Chriſt the light of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, that he ſhould be the ſalvation vnto the end of the world: It is ſaid, that they were glad, and glorified the word of the Lord. For what avayleth it a man to heare that there is ſalvation for men in Chriſt, &amp; that there is an vnſpeakable felicitie layed vp in the heavens, except that he know that he is one of the men for whom it is prepared: thoſe mens religion that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth only in the certaine knowledge that there is a Saviour, and that there is remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes in his blood, and eternall life to all that beleeue in him, and yet never la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored to know if he was given to them a Saviour in perticular vnto the remiſſion of their ſinnes, and giving of eternall life to them in particular, is nothing but a fantaſie without fruits or comfort. Here is then the chief poynt, that this life is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relie kept, &amp; that for vs. Neither can ever the ſoule of a poore ſinner receiue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, vntill it be ſaid to his ſoule, to thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth remiſſion of ſinnes, and to thee is reſerved ſalvation in the heavens. Then is his heart eſtabliſhed in hope. Thus much now for the ſuertie of our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Now followeth the ſure keeping of vs to it: and this is brought by way of a deſcription of the Saintes. For when the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:177173:55"/>Apoſtle had ſaid, that this inheritance is kept in the heaven for vs, then he expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth whom hee doth vnderſtand by that word <hi>vs,</hi> even thoſe (ſaith he) who are kept by the power of God through faith vnto ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is prepared to be ſhewed in the laſt time. So that theſe words doe both containe a deſcription of the children of God, and in their deſcription, a declareati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſuretie vnto life. The firſt point of this deſcription ſtandeth in their kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping: the ſecond in the power whereby they are kept. The third, in the meane whereby this power doth keep them. And laſtlie, the end wherefore they are kept. As concerning their keeping, it is a matter of great moment to the child of God, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he knoweth that his life be ſure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, becauſe it is in heaven, and there kept with Chriſt in God, for him, yet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is his peace and ioy troubled: becauſe he himſelfe is yet in the earth, ſubiect and exponed to the tentations of Sathan, of the world, and of the fleſh: and daylie in daunger to bee overcome, and ſo to bee ſpoyled from that life, that is ſure in the heavens. Being therefore in this daunger, and by experience trying oftimes his own weaknes, and the ſtrength of his enemies, in his manifeſt ſlydings and fallings: never can he have ſolide comfort, till his minde be aſſured, that the gates of hell ſhall not bee able to prevaile againſt him:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.8. &amp;c.</note> finding the power of God magnified in his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:177173:55"/>bodie, in that (though hee bee affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted on everie ſide) yet hee is not in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres: though hee be in doubt, yet hee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paireth not: though hee bee perſecuted, yet hee is never forſaken: and although hee bee oft caſt downe, yet hee periſheth not. They that truſt in the Lord, being as Mount Sion, which can not bee remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but remaineth for ever. So that they may ſing in that ſong of the Saintes in the hundreth and twentie nyne Pſalme:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 129.1.</note> 
               <hi>They have oftentymes afflicted mee from my youth, May Iſraell now ſay. They have oftentimes aſſlicted mee from my youth, but they could not prevaile againſt me.</hi> For the ſame God, who hath taken the keeping of ourlyfe, hath alſo taken the keeping of vs to that lyfe. Therefore the Apoſtle Paul, who reioyceth in this,
<note place="margin">2 Timoth. 1.12. 2 Timoth. 4.18.</note> that God, to whom hee had committed his lyfe, was able to keepe it vnto that day: doth alſo boldlie glorie in this aſſurance: That the Lord will deliver him from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie evill worke, and will preſerve him vnto his heavenlie kingdome. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour willing to comfort vs, againſt the griefe of his bodilie departure out of this worlde, before his death,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.11.15.</note> did recommend vs all, who are in this worlde, to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers keeping, leaſt wee should thinke our ſelves left withou a keeper, when hee who whyle hee was in the world, did keepe vs, was no more in the worlde. It is impoſſible that the Father should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney the Sonn any thing, that he shall aſke:
<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.42.</note> for the Father heareth the Sonne alwayes.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:177173:56"/>Chriſt Ieſus likewiſe in the tenth of Iohn, ſpeaking of the ſure felicity of his ſheepe, that they ſhould never periſh: he giveth the reaſon, from the ſure keeping of them in the hande of the Father. <hi>My Father</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which gave them mee, is greater then all: and none is able to take them out of my Fathers hande. Neither</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>ſhal one plucke them out of my handes.</hi> And he addeth likewyſe the reaſon. <hi>For I</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and my Father (who is ſtronger then all) are one.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Saints are kept by the power of God.</note> The ſecond point of our conſolation, is, from the power whereby God doeth keepe vs, even the power of God himſelfe. The reaſon why the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this is requiſite, may well bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the ſixt to the Epheſians, where the Apoſtle exhorting vs to arme our ſelves with this power of the Lords might, doeth give vs a reaſon why wee ſhould doe ſo, <hi>becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we wrestle not againſt fleſhe and blood, but against Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, against Powers, &amp; againſt worldly Governours, the princes of darknes of this world, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſes, which are in the high places.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he biddeth vs, <hi>To take the whole armour of God.</hi> If wee had only to doe with fleſh and blood, it might be that the power of flesh &amp; blood might be ſufficient for vs, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs: for ther is not, nor hath bene, any power of man ſo great, but there hath bene and ſhalbe a power of man able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande it. So if a Prince did ryſe againſt vs, we might flie vnder the ſhadow of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes winges for our ſecuritie, but
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:177173:56"/>no man, in the world, how great ſo ever he be, is abls to defend him ſelfe, much leſſe others, from the aſſaultes of Sathan, ſinne, and death. Theſe three are ſtronger then any creature. for ſinne hath overcome both Man and Angell and death, by ſinne, and Sathan prevailed againſt man in his integritie. Therefore it is moſt needfull that wee bee guarded by another power ſtronger then the power of man, yea ſtronger then the power of Angells, and yet ſtronger then the power of ſinne and death, which haue gotten dominion over all men, and over a great many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells. Now, a greater power then theſe is not, except only the power of God: who is able only to ſubdue all things to himſelfe, by the power of his might. This ſerveth firſt to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort vs againſt all terrour of the Divells power and malice,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> who as ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Goeth about like a roaring Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeeking whom he may devoure.</hi> knowing that we are kept by that ſtronger one, who is able to binde that ſtrong one, that is,
<note place="margin">Heb 2.14.</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and ſpoyle him of his goods, even by that mightie Sampſon, who by his owne death did deſtroy him that had the power of death, that is the Divell: and by that ſtrong Lyon of the Tribe of Iuda.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.5.9.10.</note> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, it teacheth vs that leſſon of the Apoſtle to the Corinthes, not to reioyce of our ſelves, except it bee of our infirmities, in the which we gladlie ought to reioyce, that the power of Chriſt may dwell in vs.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:177173:57"/>Moreover, even in our infirmities, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches, in neceſſities, in perſecutions, in anguiſh for Chriſtes ſake, we ſhould take pleaſure: becauſe when we are weak, then are we eſtronge: for the power of God is made perfite through weaknes, as ſheweth the ſame Apoſtle in the ſame place. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this ſheweth the vanitie of all thoſe men, who doe eſteeme them ſelues ſure ynough guarded againſt the power of the Devill, by Croſſings, by holy water, by rin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of Belles, &amp;c. and ſuch like vanities. It is evident that theſe men did never yet ſufficientlie know, either their own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or the Devills power: againſt the which by the Apoſtle in the place aforeſaid to the Epheſians, it is manifeſt, that no man is able to ſtand faſt, who is not armed and made ſtrong by the power of Gods might. It is moſt certaine, that Angells are not able to keepe vs, If God did withdraw his ſtrength from vs. And therefore doth David ſhew vs, that only the man who dwelleth in the ſecret of the moſt high, &amp; abideth in the ſhadow of the Almightie, is in a ſecure eſtate, that he needeth not to be affrayd,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.</note> neither of the feare of the night, nor of the arrow that flyeth by day: nor of the peſtilence that walketh in the darknes, nor of the plague that deſtroyeth at noone day. He shall walke vpon the Lyon and Aſpe: the yong Lyon and the Dragon shall he tread vnderfoote, becauſe the Lord will deliver him from the ſnare
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:177173:57"/>of the hunter, and from the noyſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, and will ſuffer none evill to come neare him: for he is with him in trouble to deliver him and to glorifie him. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may all the children of God boldly boaſt with the Apoſtle, of their ſecuritie,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.31. &amp;c.</note> that no Devill, nor other accuſer dare lay anie thing to their charge: ſeeing God doth iuſtifie them, no creature nor Prince, nor power ſhalbe able to condemne them, for whom Chriſt hath died, for whom he is riſen, and for whom at the right hande of the Father hee maketh interceſſion. None ſhalbe able to ſeparate them from the love of Chriſt: no not tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor anguiſh, nor perſecution, nor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, nor nakednes, nor perill, nor ſword: in all which things, ſaieth the Apoſtle, we are more then conquerors. But how? not by our owne might, not by the might of Angells, or any other creatures, but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough him that loved vs: and therefore in the gloriation of faith, doeth he defie all Principalities and powers, and Angells, &amp; life and death, thinges preſent, thinges to come: highnes, deepnes, and all creatures, becauſe he is perſuadeth, that none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is able to ſeperate him from the love of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord. For if God bee on our ſide, who can be againſt vs? the power of God keepeth vs, againſt which no power is able to ſtande. The laſt vſe of this is, to make vs afraid of ſinne, &amp; of the power of it, ſince no power of the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:177173:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>world is able to keepe vs from the power of ſinne and tentations of the Devill, of the fleſh, and of the world, except only the power of God him ſelf: and therfore they are wonderfullie deceyved, that thinke it ſtandeth in mans owne power and in the ſtrength of his owne will, to preſerve him ſelfe from ſinne, and to keepe him ſelfe in well doing. Let vs learne to flie vnto God, as our onely keeper, who by his owne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer defendeth vs from all our enemies. Nowe followeth the meane or middes, whereby this power of God is exerciſed &amp; practiſed in keeping of vs,
<note place="margin">Gods pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by faith.</note> and that is faith ſaith the Apoſtle. Who are kept, ſaith he, by the power of God through faith. So it is faith in and throw which the power of God keepeth vs. There be manie midſes and meanes in and by which the Lord vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth his power in preſervation of his creatures from bodilie &amp; temporall daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and keeping of them in the ſtrength, and enioying of this preſent life: he vſeth his creatures for nouriſhing vs in this mortall life: He employeth divers meanes for our deliverance from ſicknes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther troubles, as Medecine, and ſuch like worldlie helpes. And he manifeſteth his power in the governement of thinges in the creatures, both heavenlie and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. In all which it may be iuſtlie ſaid, that God by his power doth keepe all things in the life, ſtate and condition wherein hee putteth them: but none of al theſe meanes
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:177173:58"/>doe ſerve to keepe vs from ſpirituall eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies vnto eternall life: there is another meane whereby God vttereth his power, and exerciſeth it in vs to keepe vs from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death vnto ſalvation, and that is faith. Therefore is it that the Apoſtle writing to the Epheſians,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.19.</note> prayeth to God for them, that the eyes of their vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding might be opened, to knowe what is the exceeding greatnes of his power to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs which beleeve according to the working of his mightie power which he wrought in Chriſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he raiſed him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, to teach vs, that God vttereth his power &amp; practiſes it in his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by faith. And that this power which he exerciſeth in vs that beleeve, is a more ſtrong power then any that ever God vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or manifeſted in anie other of his workes, either in creating all things of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or yet in governing or preſerving all things created. For the power &amp; might which he imployeth to our preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on who beleeve, is that ſame power and ſtrength whiche hee wrought in rayſinge Chriſt from the dead, and in glorifying him, and making him the head of all Principalitie &amp; Power, and giving him to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of his church. Which we in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meaſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ever it was vttered in any other work, becauſe it muſt be greater that maketh Chriſt the head of all power in ſubdewing all things vnder his feete, then that power which made all other powers.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:177173:59"/>Seeing the power of Chriſt given him by the Father, over all Thrones and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, over Devills and Angells, and ſinne and death, is greater then all other powers which is ſubdued vnder his feet. Therefore the Apoſtle ſpeaking of this power of God towards vs that beleeve, ſaith, That it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the working of the ſtrength of his power, as though God never had exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed the ſtrength of his power, in the ſtrength thereof, but in Chriſt our head, &amp; in vs that beleeve. And therefore alſo our faith whereby this power of God is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in vs, both in quickning and rayſing vs from the dead with Chriſt, and in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving vs, is called by the Apoſtle to the Coloſſians,
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.12</note> 
               <hi>The faith of the operation of God:</hi> or rather, <hi>of the effectuall working of God.</hi> In the which place the Apoſtle ſheweth plainlie, that it is through this faith of the operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, that God doth raiſe vs from the dead, as he did Chriſt. Letting vs knowe, that as it is the power of God onely, that is able to worke theſe things in vs that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne eternall life: ſo this power is never performed, nor practiſed in vs, but throw faith. For this cauſe is it that the Apoſtle to the Philippians,
<note place="margin">Philip. 1.27</note> declaring to vs how wee muſt fight, and with what armour againſt all tentations and perſecutions, he biddeth vs fight togither through the faith of the Goſpell.
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.9.</note> And the Apoſtle Peter, teaching vs how to reſiſt our adverſarie the Devill, willeth vs to Reſiſt him by ſtedfaſtneſſe of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:177173:59"/>faith. And al this is to declare vnto vs, that there is no ſuretie, nor ſure keeping of vs againſt the Devil, the world, and ſinne, but by faith onely: according to that which Iohn in his firſt epiſtle teacheth vs,
<note place="margin">1 Ioh 5.4.5</note> 
               <hi>This is that victorie, that overcometh this world, even our faith.</hi> For who is it that overcommeth this world, but he which beleeveth that Ieſus is that ſonne of God. And the Apoſtle to the Epheſians cap. 6. verſ. 16. knowing that our chief ſtrength ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in our faith, biddeth vs above all other partes of our ſpirituall armour, <hi>to take the ſhield of faith, wherewith wee may quenche all the firie dartes of the wicked.</hi> And Chriſt when hee declareth vnto his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<note place="margin">Luc. 22.31.</note> that Sathan had deſired to winow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as wheat, he ſaith to Peter: <hi>but I have prayed for thee, that thy faith faile not.</hi> Hereby ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that howſoever the Devill aſſault vs, &amp; buffet vs, yet in none of our ſlydings obtai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth he a full victorie, ſo long as our faith faileth not: and that in the ſure continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of our faith, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth our ſure keeping from all the Devills ſifting and winowing of vs. Hereby it is manifeſt, that they which never beleved, had never proofe of the ſaving power of God, and that they whoſe faith is nothing powerful in opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt Sathan, and ſinne, never had anie true faith: but as Iames ſaieth, <hi>Their faith is nothing but a dead faith.</hi> For they who truely beleeve, doe finde in them ſelves a power effectuall, whereby they are made able to fight againſt all Principalities and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:177173:60"/>ſpirituall wickedneſſes: and not only to fight, but alſo to overcome them. So that even it is a wonder to the Saintes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who knowe their <hi>weacknes naturall,</hi> that they ſhold be ſo ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthned by grace, that nothing is able to overcome them. The vſe of all this is, to teach vs, that aboue all things, we ſhould pray to God, to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our faith, and to preſerve it, that it fayle not. For according to the meaſure of our faith, ſo is the meaſure of our ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth: and according as we continew in faith, ſo doth our ſtrength continue with vs. As by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie, our faith fayling, our ſtrength faileth vs. Therefore was it that Peter, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he receyved a great foyle from the Devill in denying his Lord, yet did he at length overcome the Devill, becauſe his faith failed not, though hee failed in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. The ſpirit of God in the 11. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Hebrewes ſheweth that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Saintes were able to doe or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for the glory of God, it was by faith: &amp; therefore is it no wonder, although the wicked be overcome with every tentation, to luſt, to drunkenes, to chambering, to wantonnes, pryde and covetouſnes, &amp;c. ſeeing the power of God, by which theſe things only can be overcome, is not in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they being without faith.</p>
            <p>Now have we to ſpeak of the end wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we are kept,
<note place="margin">The Saints are kept to ſalvation.</note> that is, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalvation,</hi> as we ſaid before of the keeping
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:177173:60"/>of our life: That it were no comfort to vs, except it were kept for vs. So likewiſe of vs, it were no matter of ioy to vs, that wee are kept, if it were not to ſalvation that we are kept. For God doth keepe the very De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills in chaines vnder darknes. But where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
<note place="margin">Iud. 6.</note> vnto the condemnation of the great day, ſayeth <hi>Iude.</hi> Even ſo alſo doeth he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the wicked from many evills in this lyfe, but all that keeping is no comfort, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are kept as beaſtes for the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vnto the day of wrath, and manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the iuſt iudgement of God. But here is the comfort of the Saints, that God keepeth them vnto ſalvation, becauſe he keepeth them by his power, through faith. And this alſo ſerveth to confirme vs in the aſſurance of inioying this lyfe, becauſe it is both for vs that the Lord keepeth it: and it is vnto vs that hee kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vs. That it is impoſſible to fruſtrate vs of it, though all the world ſhould bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs. That ſame which the Apoſtle before did call, <hi>a lively hope, and an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance immortall, &amp;c.</hi> that ſame doth hee call nowe, <hi>ſalvation:</hi> to teach vs, that our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance is ſalvation, and that ſalvation is our inheritance. For no man can bee Gods heire, but he muſt inherite life: and none can inherite lyfe, but hee muſt bee the heire of GOD, and Coheire with Chriſt. This for the ſurety of this lyfe, to the hope wherof the Lord our God beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:177173:61"/>
            <p> Now the laſt poynt is, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of this ſalvation. Touching the which there is three things to be marked. Firſt, that this ſalvation is alreadie prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dlie, that it is to be revealed. And thirdlie, the time of the revealing of it, is the laſt day. To come to the firſt, it is not to be thought that our ſalvation is not yet readie,
<note place="margin">Salvation is now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</note> although we be not yet in poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it. Indeed before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt in the fleſh, ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not prepared, nor made readie for vs. For Chriſt was the high Prieſt of good things to come,
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.10.11.</note> &amp; his time is called <hi>the time of Reformation:</hi> for the way to the moſt holy place was not yet ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whyle as yet the firſt tabernacle was ſtanding, neither was that ſacrifice offered that doth purge our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences from dead workes, to ſerve the living God, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by eternall redemption is purchaſed. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was our foreru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner entred in before vs into the heavens for vs, to prepare a place for vs, in purifying the heavenly things themſelves with his owne ſacrifice. For the Lawe had but the ſhadow of good things to come, and not the verie Image of the things. But nowe ſince our Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is offered, and our Advocat entred into the heavens, and crowned with glorie and honour in the fleſh, ſo taking poſſeſſion in his very manhood, of this inheritance im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, vndefiled, and which withereth not. Now, I ſay, ſaluation is made readie. Neither is it holden back from vs, nor we
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:177173:61"/>from it, becauſe it is not yet prepared, but becauſe the time is not yet come in the which we muſt receyve it.
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.39.40.</note> For as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers received not the promiſe, God provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a better thing for vs, that they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vs ſhould not be made perfite, even ſo now, we receive not the inheritance pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, God providing a better thing for the Saints, yet to be borne vnto the end of the world, that we without them ſhould not be made perfite. For they receyved not by <hi>Moſes</hi> the promiſed Meſſias, leaſt they only ſhould have bin ſaved &amp; not the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles alſo. Therefore did he not come vnto the end of that diſpenſation, at which time the Gentiles alſo were to bee called. God perſuading <hi>Iaphet</hi> to dwell in the tentes of <hi>Sem:</hi> even ſo now though Chriſt be made a light to the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles aſwel as to the Iewes: and ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the endes of the world, &amp; that he hath alreadie finiſhed the works and purchaſed ſalvation, yet doe we not receive it vntill all thoſe for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, be made readie aſwell as we. In the Revelation, the ſoules of them which are killed for the word of God, and for the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie which they mainteyned, when they cried with a loude voyce, ſaying:
<note place="margin">Revel. 6.10 11.</note> 
               <hi>How long Lord which art holy and true, doest not thou iudge and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth?</hi> It was anſwered to them, <hi>That they ſhould rest for a little ſeaſon, vntill their fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaunts and their brethren, that ſhould be killed even as they, were fulfilled.</hi> For both the full ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:177173:62"/>of the wicked, and full glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and redemption of the Saints, is delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vntill the number, both of the wicked and redeemed, bee fulfilled. This ſerveth to comfort vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we know that our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is not now to be prepared, &amp; to be purchaſed as yet, but that it is readie and prepared already: So that, if we were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for it, it is ready for vs. There is no lett therefore in our ſalvation, why we enioy it not, for it is ready prepared, even as a bryd ready for her bridgrome, but we are not yet readie, becauſe we wante yet a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe with whom we muſt enioy it, &amp; who with vs muſt enioy it. For it is not kept for me alone, nor for vs of this age a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, or for vs of this or that Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone, but it is kept for vs al who belong to Ieſus Chriſt, as members of his bodie: which muſt bee completed and accompliſhed in all the members, not one wanting, before it put on the glorie of the head. Next ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>It is prepared to be revealed or ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed.</hi> This yet ſerveth to increaſe our ioy. It was doubtles a forcible argument, that Chriſt vſed, to eaſe the hearts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<note place="margin">Salvation shalbe revea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led.</note> and ſettle them from the griefe and trouble conceaved at the newes of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from them, when hee tolde them, <hi>That he did goe to prepare a place for them:</hi> but it doubled their ioye,
<note place="margin">Iohn 14.2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> when he added, <hi>That he would come againe, and receive them vnto himſelf, that where he is, they might be alſo.</hi> So doubtles it is with vs. It is no ſmal matter of Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:177173:62"/>when we know that ſalvation is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs by Ieſus Chriſt in the heavens: but it doeth much more glad our heartes, when it is tolde vs that this ſalvation of ours, which now is hid from our eyes, shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be shewed to vs, that wee may ſee it with our eyes. <hi>Simeon</hi> with al the reſt of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, reioyced in the promiſe made to them of the Meſſias. But Simeon had this more then the reſt, that he had this promiſe, that hee should not ſee death, before hee had ſeene the annoynted of the Lord: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as all did die with ioy ſufficient in the promiſe of his comming, yet Simeon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoved to have more ioy in his death, when he ſaid: <hi>Lord now letteſt thou thy ſervaunt depart in peace, according to thy worde: For my eyes have ſeene thy ſalvation.</hi> No ſurely, it were no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to vs to know that there is ſalvation in the heavens, if we were ſecluded for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from ſeeing that ſalvation: yea it were better for the wicked never to have known there were a God: yea that there were not a God at all, then to be banished from the preſence of that God for ever, as they shall be.</p>
            <p>The vſe hereof is, to comfort vs againſt the preſent longinge and earneſt deſire wee have of the ſight of God, and of our Saviour, and of that glory,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.2.</note> whyle wee ſighe. Deſiring to bee clothed with our houſe which is from heaven: even that we know that our life which is now hid with Chriſt in God, shall once bee manifeſted.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:177173:63"/>For during this life, neither are we ſeene to the world the children of God: neither is our ſalvation ſeene of vs.
<note place="margin">Iohn 3.2.</note> For as Iohn ſaith, Though now we bee the children of God, yet it is not made manifeſt, what wee ſhalbe,
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.4.</note> but when Chriſt which is our life ſhal appeare, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal we alſo appeare with him in glorie. And therefore is it, that the fervent deſire of the creature wayteth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſonnes of God ſhalbe revealed.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.19.</note> And we our ſelves are ſaid to be ſaved by hope, and that for this cauſe wee doe ſighe and groane in our ſelves, waiting for the adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, even the redemption of our bodie. Now the time when our ſalvation shalbe shewed,
<note place="margin">Salvation ſhalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt.</note> is, the laſt time. For ſo long as Chriſt is hid, ſo long muſt our ſalvation be hid: for without him, it can never be ſeen, for he is our ſalvation: and therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt is not to be ſeene againe vntill the laſt time, our life ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be ſeene vntill that time. This is the cauſe that the Saints doe crie with a moſt earneſt deſire: <hi>Come Lord Ieſus, come:</hi> and that that day, which is the laſt of al days, may come, becauſe they know their life ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be revealed till that day. This day of all dayes is the moſt lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for by the godlie: and of all dayes leaſt deſired or wished of the worlde. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is evident, The godlie doe know that that bringeth to them the end of all miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and everlaſting ioye: whereas to the wicked it bringeth an end of al their flesh lie pleaſures and worldlie delites, wherein
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:177173:63"/>they did put their felicitie, and doth begin their endles damnation, Therefore would they wiſh it never came: So co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie is the deſire of Gods children to the deſire of the wicked. For ther ſhalbe two things in that day revealed that never were ſeen before, that is, the ſalvation of the elect, and the vengeance prepared for the wicked. It is true in deed that God ſheweth his ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, even in this world, in all the deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his children, like as hee ſheweth his vengeance in al plagues powred vpon the wicked: but we muſt diſtinguish betwixt al ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enioyed in this life, &amp; that ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is to be manifeſted in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt: and betwixt all iudgements in this life, &amp; that iudgement that shalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the appearing of the Lord in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire. For neither is the firſt that full fruit of Gods mercie purchaſed by Chriſt, neither is the other the iuſt reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence of Gods Iuſtice to the wicked. And therefore is it in the ſcript. that the life of the Saints, is ſaid to be hid vntill the laſt time: and the wrath of God and his Iuſtice to be hid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the day of wrath, and manifeſtation of the iuſt iudgement of God.
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note> For that day is the day both of the manifeſtation of Gods iuſt iudgement, and of this riches of his mercie. This teacheth vs to have patience in this preſent life: although our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition in Chriſt be not knowen of the world, nor we accompted of, as the children of God: although here we be eſteemed the offſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:177173:64"/>of the worlde, and the contempt of men, for our eſtate is not yet manifeſted. As likewiſe it teacheth vs to reioyce, the more neare the day of Gods iudgement be: becauſe our redemption is the nearer. Yea this maketh that the godlie do more glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie depart out of this life, then to remaine in it. Whereas the wicked eſteemeth it a hell to ſpeak to them either of death, or of Chriſtes comming againe to iudge the world. Happie is the man that is begotten to this livelie hope, for he findeth what comfort is in both: while as the wicked ſhall wiſhe that the mountaynes might fall vpon them, and the earth open and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, rather then they ſhould ſee the day of Chriſtes appearing. But let vs who beleeve and knowes that our life and ſalvation commeth with Chriſt. Let vs I ſay with all our hearts pray Lord Ieſus come, come Lord Ieſus come, even ſo bee it, <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177173:64"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
